这个世界改变了
The world is changed.
我从水中触摸到
I feel it in the water.
我从地上感觉到
I feel it in the earth.
我从空气中嗅到
I smell it in the air.
过去的一切
Much that once was...
都已失落
...is lost.
现在已经没人记得了
For none now live who remember it.
魔  戒
这一切都从铸造魔戒开始
It began with the forging of the Great Rings.
精灵族得到三只戒指
Three were given to the Elves.
他们长生不老 也是最有智慧最公平的种族
Immortal,wisest and fairest of all beings.
矮人族分到七只戒指
Seven to the Dwarf-lords.
他们很会挖掘矿坑 是山洞的能工巧匠
Great miners and craftsmen of the mountain halls.
而九只
And nine...
九只戒指送给了人类
...nine rings were gifted to the race of Men...
他们比别人更渴望权力
... who,above all else,desire power.
(中土世界)
每只戒指都拥有统治每个种族的力量
For within these rings was bound the strength and will to govern each race.
但他们都受到了欺骗
But they were all of them deceived.
因为还有另一只被铸造了
For another ring was made.
在魔多末日火山的烈焰中
In the land of Mordor,in the fires of Mount Doom...
黑暗魔君索伦暗中铸造了一只至尊魔戒
... the Dark Lord Sauron forged in secret a Master Ring...
来控制一切
... to control all others.
他在至尊魔戒中注入他的邪恶 残酷
And into this Ring he poured his cruelty,his malice...
以及支配天下的可怕欲望
...and his will to dominate all life.
一只统治一切的至尊魔戒
One Ring to rule them all.
一个接一个...
One by one...
中土世界的自由之土感受到了至尊魔戒的力量
... the Free Lands of Middle-earth fell to the power of the Ring.
但是有些人群起反抗
But there were some who resisted.
人类和精灵组成了最后的同盟对抗魔多的邪恶兵团
A Last Alliance of Men and Elves marched against the armies of Mordor.
他们在险恶的末日火山为中土世界的自由奋战
And on the slopes of Mount Doom,they fought for the freedom of Middle-earth.
稳住阵线！
Tangado haid!
放箭！
Leithio i philinn!
胜利终于在望
Victory was near.
但是至尊魔戒的力量
But the power of the Ring...
无人能敌
...could not be undone.
就在这时候
It was in this moment...
当大家都失去希望之际
... when all hope had faded...
人皇之子埃西铎拾起他父亲的宝剑
... that Isildur,son of the king,took up his father's sword.
黑暗魔君索伦 中土世界自由人民之敌终于被击败
Sauron,the enemy of the Free Peoples of Middle-earth,was defeated.
至尊魔戒落入埃西铎手中
The Ring passed to Isildur...
他只有一次机会永远摧毁邪恶
... who had this one chance to destroy evil forever.
但是人心
But the hearts of Men...
很容易受到蛊惑
...are easily corrupted.
而且至尊魔戒有它自己的意志
And the Ring of Power has a will of its own.
它背叛了埃西铎
It betrayed Isildur...
最后害死了他
... to his death.
不该被遗忘的东西
And some things that should not have been forgotten...
也遗忘了
... were lost.
历史成为传说
History became legend...
传说成为神话
...legend became myth.
两千五百年来
And fortwo and a half thousand years...
至尊魔戒的下落无人得知
... the Ring passed out of all knowledge.
直到机会到来
Until,when chance came...
让它蛊惑一个新的持有者
...it ensnared a new bearer.
我的宝贝
My precious.
至尊魔戒落入咕噜手中
The Ring came to the creature Gollum...
他把它带到迷雾山脉的洞穴中
... who took it deep into the tunnels of the Misty Mountains.
他的身心完全被魔戒占据
And there it consumed him.
它落到我手中
It came to me.
我的 我的爱 是我的
My own. My Iove. My own.
我的宝贝
My precious.
魔戒让咕噜得到违反自然的长寿
The Ring brought to Gollum unnatural long life.
五百年来它扭曲他的心智
For 500 years it poisoned his mind.
它在咕噜阴暗的洞穴中静静地等待着
And in the gloom of Gollum's cave,it waited.
黑暗再度笼罩大地
Darkness crept back into the forests of the world.
谣传东方升起邪恶力量
Rumor grew of a shadow in the East...
人们心中产生无名的恐惧
... whispers of a nameless fear.
于是至尊魔戒知道
And the Ring of Power perceived...
它即将再度现身
...its time had now come.
它舍弃了咕噜
It abandoned Gollum.
但是出乎至尊魔戒的意料之外
But something happened then the Ring did not intend.
它被一个最料想不到的人捡到
It was picked up by the most unlikely creature imaginable.
这是什么？
What's this?
一个哈比人
A Hobbit.
夏尔的比尔博・巴金斯
Bilbo Baggins of the Shire.
一只戒指
A ring.
不见了！
Lost!
我的宝贝不见了！
My precious is Iost!
不久的将来...
For the time will soon come...
哈比人将决定世界的命运
... when Hobbits will shape the fortunes of all.
(瑞文戴尔)
9月的第22天
The 22nd day of September...
1400年
...in the year 1 400...
(哈比屯)
以夏尔历法计算
...by Shire-reckoning.
(夏尔)
哈比屯西区 巴榭路 袋底洞
Bag End,Bagshot Row,Hobbiton,Westfarthing...
(伊利雅德)
夏尔
...the Shire...
中土世界
...Middle-earth.
世界第三纪元
The Third Age of this world.
护 戒 使 者
去而复返
There and Back Again.'
哈比人的故事
A Hobbit's Tale.
比尔博・巴金斯著
By Bilbo Baggins.
（去而复返：哈比人的故事 比尔博・巴金斯著）
现在...
Now...
该从何说起呢？
...where to begin?
对了
Ah,yes....
关于...
"Concerning...
（关于哈比人）
哈比人
...Hobbits."
哈比人一直都在夏尔的四个区开垦种植 安居乐业
Hobbits have been living and farming in the four Farthings of the Shire...
数百年来
...for many hundreds of years...
都乐于遗忘并被世人遗忘
...quite content to ignore and be ignored...
也就是世上的其他人种
...by the world of the Big Folk.
毕竟中土世界充满不计其数的奇怪生物
Middle-earth being,after all,full of strange creatures beyond count...
哈比人的存在微不足道
...Hobbits must seem of little importance...
他们并非骁勇善战的勇士
...being neither renowned as great warriors...
也不算是聪明绝顶的智者
...nor counted among the very wise.
佛罗多！有人敲门
Frodo! Someone at the door.
事实上 有人说
In fact,it has been remarked by some...
哈比人唯一真正热爱的就是食物
... that Hobbits' only real passion is for food.
但这是很不公平的说法
A rather unfair observation...
因为我们也很喜欢酿麦酒
...as we have also developed a keen interest in the brewing of ales...
还有抽烟草
...and the smoking of pipe-weed.
但是我们内心的真爱
But where our hearts truly lie...
就是和平宁静
...is in peace and quiet...
还有肥沃的土地
...and good,tilled earth.
每一个哈比人都热爱种植生长的东西
For all Hobbits share a love of things that grow.
别人一定会觉得我们的日子过得太悠闲
And,yes,no doubt to others,our ways seem quaint.
但是今天更是印证了我的想法
But today of all days,it is brought home to me.'
能过朴实简单的生活真的是一种幸福
It is no bad thing to celebrate a simple life.
（生日快乐比尔博・巴金斯）
佛罗多 开门！
Frodo,the door!
讨厌 那小子呢？
Sticklebacks. Where is that boy?
佛罗多！
Frodo!
外面风景多美丽
Down from the door where it began
我要踏上这旅程
And I must follow if I can
眼前道路无止尽
The road goes ever on and on
蜿蜒崎岖又漫长
Down from the door where it began
虽然路程尚遥远
Now far ahead the road has gone
我必须继续前进
And I must follow if I can
你迟到了
You're late.
巫师绝对不会迟到 佛罗多・巴金斯
A wizard is never late,Frodo Baggins.
他也不会早到 他一定是按照计划准时到
Nor is he early. He arrives precisely when he means to.
见到你太好了 甘道夫！
It's wonderful to see you,Gandalf!
我怎么会错过你比尔博叔叔的生日？
You didn't think I'd miss your Uncle Bilbo's birthday?
那老不死还好吧？
How is the old rascal?
我听说生日宴会非常盛大
I hear it's going to be a party of special magnificence.
你也了解比尔博 他把这儿搞得鸡飞狗跳
You know Bilbo. He's got the whole place in an uproar.
这样他应该高兴了
Well,that should please him.
夏尔有一半人都被邀请了
Half the Shire's been invited.
另外一半也不请自来
And the rest of them are turning up anyway.
夏尔的生活就这样继续着
And so life in the Shire goes on...
从古到今都一样
... very much as it has this past Age...
自给自足 快乐幸福 没有什么太大的改变
...full of its own comings and goings,with change coming slowly.
或许永远也不会有所改变
If it comes at all.
因为夏尔的一切历久弥新
For things are made to endure in the Shire...
一代一代地传下去
...passing from one generation to the next.
巴金斯家族一直都有成员住在山丘下的
There's always been a Baggins living here under the Hill...
袋底洞
...in Bag End.
以后也一定会有
And there always will be.
不过说实话 最近比尔博有点怪
To tell you the truth,Bilbo's been a bit odd lately.
我是说 比以前更怪
I mean,more than usual.
他成天把自己关在书房
He's taken to Iocking himself in his study.
我每次趁他不注意都看到他在研究古地图
He spends hours poring over old maps when he thinks I'm not looking.
它跑哪儿去了？
Where's it gone?
他一定在搞什么名堂
He's up to something.
好吧 你不说拉倒
All right,then. Keep your secrets.
什么？
What?
我知道你一定脱不了关系
But I know you have something to do with it.
真是的
Good gracious me.
在你出现前 巴金斯家族一向都很规矩
Before you came along,we Bagginses were very well thought of.
确实
Indeed.
我们从不冒险或做意外的事
Never had any adventures or did anything unexpected.
如果你指的是关于龙的那件事 我只是勉强牵涉
If you're referring to the incident with the dragon,I was barely involved.
我所做的只是轻轻地把你叔叔推出门外
All I did was give your uncle a Iittle nudge out of the door.
不管怎样你都被正式列为捣乱份子
Whatever you did,you've been officially labeled a disturber of the peace.
真的吗？
Oh,really?
甘道夫！甘道夫！
Gandalf! Gandalf!
放烟火 甘道夫
Fireworks,Gandalf!
甘道夫！放烟火 甘道夫！
Gandalf! Fireworks,Gandalf!
甘道夫？
Gandalf?
你回来了我好高兴
I'm glad you're back.
我也是 好孩子
So am I,dear boy.
我也是
So am I.
（与晚会无关者免进）
不要 谢谢！
No,thank you!
我们不欢迎访客 祝寿者或远亲！
We don't want any more visitors,well-wishers or distant relations!
那么一个非常老的朋友呢？
And what about very old friends?
甘道夫？
Gandalf?
比尔博・巴金斯
Bilbo Baggins.
亲爱的甘道夫
My dear Gandalf!
见到你真好 111岁大寿！谁会相信？
Good to see you. 111 years old! Who would believe it?
你一点都没老
You haven't aged a day.
快点 进来吧！
Come on,come in!
欢迎 欢迎
Welcome,welcome.
来吧
Oh,here we are.
茶？还是来烈一点的？
Tea? Or maybe something a Iittle stronger?
我还有几瓶1296年的陈年好酒
I've got a few bottles of the OId Winyard Ieft. 1296.
很好的年份 几乎跟我一样老
Very good year. Almost as old as I am.
我老爹珍藏的 打开一瓶如何？
It was laid down by my father. What say we open one,eh?
茶就行 谢谢
Just tea,thank you.
你上个礼拜就该到了
I was expecting you sometime last week.
没关系 你一向想来就来 想走就走
Not that it matters. You come and go as you please. AIways have and always will.
只是让我有点措手不及 家里只有冻鸡和腌菜
You caught me a bit unprepared. We've only got cold chicken and a bit of pickle....
还有乳酪 不行 太寒酸了
There's some cheese here. No,that won't do.
我们有覆盆子果酱 苹果馅饼
We've got raspberry jam,an apple tart....
但是好像还不太够 哦 没事 没问题
But not much for afters. Oh,no,we're all right.
我找到一些海绵蛋糕
I've just found some sponge cake.
(孤山)
我可以煮几个蛋 如果你...
I could make you some eggs if you'd--
甘...
Gan...
茶就行 谢谢
Just tea,thank you.
好吧
Oh,right.
你不介意我吃吧？
You don't mind if I eat,do you?
不 尽管吃吧
No,not at all.
比尔博！比尔博・巴金斯！
Bilbo! Bilbo Baggins!
说我不在家！
I'm not at home!
是塞克维尔・巴金斯
It's the Sackville-Bagginses.
我知道你在那里！
I know you're in there!
他们在房子后面
They're after the house.
他们一直不原谅我在这里住这么长时间
They've never forgiven me for Iiving this Iong.
我被这些像苍蝇成天黏着我的亲戚
I've got to get away from these confounded relatives,hanging on the bell all day...
吵得一刻不得安宁
...never giving me a moment's peace.
我好想再看到高山
I want to see mountains again.
高山 甘道夫！
Mountains,Gandalf!
然后找一个安静的地方写完我的书
And then find somewhere quiet where I can finish my book.
哦 茶
Oh,tea.
所以你想要实现你的计划？
So you mean to go through with your plan?
对 对 一切都在掌握中
Yes,yes. It's all in hand.
全都安排好了
All the arrangements are made.
谢谢
Oh,thank you.
佛罗多有些怀疑
Frodo suspects something.
当然了 他可是巴金斯家的人
Of course he does. He's a Baggins...
不是硬瓶家的笨小孩
...not some blockheaded Bracegirdle from Hardbottle.
你会告诉他吧？
You will tell him,won't you?
会 会
Yes,yes.
他很喜欢你
He's very fond of you.
我知道
I know.
我开口的话他一定会跟着我去
He'd probably come with me if I asked him.
但我想佛罗多还是衷心地深爱着夏尔
I think in his heart,Frodo's still in Iove with the Shire.
绿油油的树林和土地
The woods,the fields.
潺潺的溪流
Little rivers.
我老了 甘道夫
I am old,Gandalf.
虽然我看起来并不老 但是我的心老了
I know I don't Iook it,but I'm beginning to feel it in my heart.
我的意志变得薄弱
I feel thin.
一切都索然无味
Sort of stretched...
就像面包上的黄油涂得不够多
...Iike butter scraped over too much bread.
我需要一个假期
I need a holiday.
一个非常长的假期
A very Iong holiday.
我也不期望我会回来
And I don't expect I shall return.
说实话 我不想回来
In fact,I mean not to.
老托比 南区最好的烟草
OId Toby. The finest weed in the Southfarthing.
甘道夫 我的老朋友
Gandalf,my old friend...
这将是令人难忘的一晚
...this will be a night to remember.
你好 你好
Hello,hello.
小胖博哲 很高兴见到你 欢迎 欢迎
Fatty Bolger. Lovely to see you. Welcome,welcome.
山姆 快去邀萝西跳舞
Go on,Sam. Ask Rosie for a dance.
我想再喝一杯麦酒
I think I'll just have another ale.
哦 不 你别喝了
Oh,no,you don't.
去啊！
Go on!
我站在那儿
So there I was...
面对三个可怕的巨魔
...at the mercy of three monstrous trolls.
它们吵着
And they were all arguing amongst themselves...
要怎样把我们吃掉
...about how they were going to cook us.
是一口把我们吞了 还是一个接一个把我们压扁成果冻
Whether it be turned on a spit,or to sit on us one by one,squash us into jelly.
他们喋喋不休吵个没完没了
They spent so much time arguing the whithertos and the whyfors...
结果天亮的第一道曙光
...that the sun's first Iight crept over the top of the trees...
把它们都变成了石头！
...and turned them all to stone!
快点
Quickly.
飞走了！
Up they go!
不 不 那个大的！大的！
No,the big one.
抱腹太太 很高兴见到你 欢迎 欢迎
Mrs. Bracegirdle,how nice to see you. Welcome,welcome.
这都是你的孩子吗？
Are all these children yours?
老天爷 你还真是能生啊
Good gracious,you have been productive.
比尔博？
Bilbo?
塞克维尔・巴金斯！
Sackville-Bagginses!
快躲起来！
Quickly,hide!
谢了 我的侄子
Thank you,my boy.
你是个好孩子 佛罗多
You're a good lad,Frodo.
我一直都很自私 你知道
I'm very selfish,you know.
对 我真的很自私
Yes,I am. Very selfish.
我不知道为什么我在你父母死后收养了你
I don't know why I took you in after your mother and father died...
但这并不是出于仁慈
...but it wasn't out of charity.
我想是因为
I think it was because...
在这么多亲戚里头
...of all my numerous relations...
只有你表现出了真正的精神
...you were the one Baggins that showed real spirit.
比尔博 你是不是偷喝了老爹珍藏的酿酒？
Bilbo,have you been at the Gaffer's home brew?
没有
No.
好吧 喝了 但这不是重点
Well,yes,but that's not the point.
重点是 佛罗多...
The point is,Frodo...
你一定会过得很好
...you'll be all right.
好了！
Done!
你应该把它插到地里面
You're supposed to stick it in the ground.
它是插在地里了
It is in the ground.
在外面呢！
Outside!
这都是你的主意
This was your idea.
比尔博
Bilbo.
比尔博 当心那只飞龙
Bilbo,watch out for the dragon!
飞龙？这儿有一千年没出现飞龙了
Nonsense. There hasn't been a dragon in these parts for a thousand years.
那个不错
That was good.
我们再来一个
Let's get another one.
梅里雅达克・布兰迪巴克和皮里格林・图克
Meriadoc Brandybuck and Peregrin Took.
我就知道
I might've known.
致词 比尔博！
Speech,Bilbo!
致词！
Speech!
亲爱的巴金斯家和波芬家
My dear Bagginses and Boffins...
图克家和布兰迪巴克家
...Tooks and Brandybucks...
葛卢伯家 丘伯家
...Grubbs,Chubbs...
吹号者家
...Hornblowers...
博哲家
...Bolgers...
抱腹家
...Bracegirdles...
和傲脚家
...and Proudfoots.
是傲足家！
Proudfeet!
今天是我第111个生日！
Today is my 111th birthday!
生日快乐！
Happy birthday!
但是111年的时间太短了 我真想一直跟你们在一起
But alas,eleventy-one years is far too short a time to Iive among...
这么杰出优秀的哈比人
...such excellent and admirable Hobbits.
我只认识你们一丁点
I don't know half of you half as well as I should Iike...
而你们一丁点也不值得我喜欢
...and I Iike Iess than half of you half as well as you deserve.
我有事要做
I have things to do.
我把这件事拖得太久
I've put this off far too Iong.
我遗憾地宣布宴会结束了！
I regret to announce this is the end!
我要走了
I'm going now.
我要向大家道别
I bid you all a very fond farewell.
再见
Goodbye.
我想你一定觉得这招很高明
I suppose you think that was terribly clever.
好了 甘道夫 你没看到他们的表情吗？
Come on,Gandalf. Did you see their faces?
世上有很多神奇的戒指 但是不该随便乱用
There are many magic rings in this world,and none of them should be used Iightly.
我只是开个玩笑
It was just a bit of fun.
你或许是对的 像平常一样
Oh,you're probably right,as usual.
你会留出一只眼睛照看佛罗多吧？
You will keep an eye on Frodo,won't you?
两只眼
Two eyes.
只要它们一有空闲
As often as I can spare them.
我要把一切都留给他
I'm Ieaving everything to him.
你的那只戒指呢？
What about this ring of yours?
那也留下来吗？
Is that staying too?
当然 当然
Yes,yes.
它在壁炉上面的信封里面
It's in an envelope over there on the mantelpiece.
不对 等一下 它在...
No. Wait,it's...
在我的口袋里
...here in my pocket.
不是...？不是很奇怪吗？
Isn't that--? Isn't that odd,now?
是啊 有何不可呢？
Yet,after all,why not?
我何不留着它？
Why shouldn't I keep it?
我认为你应该把戒指留下来
I think you should leave the ring behind.
有那么困难吗？
Is that so hard?
没有啊
Well,no.
当然有
And yes.
它落到我手中 我不想离开它
Now it comes to it,I don't feel Iike parting with it.
它是我的 我找到的！它落到了我手中！
It's mine. I found it! It came to me!
那没必要生气吧
There's no need to get angry.
如果我生气了 全是你的错！
Well,if I'm angry,it's your fault!
它是我的
It's mine.
我一个人的
My own.
我的宝贝
My precious.
宝贝？
Precious?
以前也有别人这么叫过它
It's been called that before,but not by you.
我自己的东西关你什么事？
What business is it of yours what I do with my own things?
我认为你留着那只戒指够久了
I think you've had that ring quite long enough.
你只想独吞它！
You want it for yourself!
比尔博・巴金斯！
Bilbo Baggins!
别把我当成一个江湖术士
Do not take me for some conjurer of cheap tricks.
我并不想抢你的东西
I am not trying to rob you.
我只是想帮助你
I'm trying to help you.
这么多年了 我们一直是朋友
All your Iong years,we've been friends.
请你像以前一样相信我
Trust me as you once did.
让它走吧
Let it go.
你说的对 甘道夫
You're right,Gandalf.
戒指一定要留给佛罗多
The ring must go to Frodo.
天色晚了 路还很长
It's late. The road is Iong.
对 是时候了
Yes,it is time.
比尔博 戒指还在你的口袋里
Bilbo,the ring is still in your pocket.
我替我的书想到一个结尾
I've thought up an ending for my book:
他从此快乐地生活下去直到他寿终正寝
"And he Iived happily ever after to the end of his days."
你一定会的 我亲爱的朋友
And I'm sure you will,my dear friend.
再见了 甘道夫
Goodbye,Gandalf.
再见了 亲爱的比尔博
Goodbye,dear Bilbo.
眼前道路无止尽
The road goes ever on and on
后会有期了
Until our next meeting.
它是我的 我一个人的
It's mine. My own.
我的宝贝
My precious.
黑暗中的谜语
Riddles in the dark.
比尔博！
Bilbo!
我的宝贝
My precious.
宝贝
Precious.
他走了 对吧？
He's gone,hasn't he?
他一直都说要离开这儿
He talked for so Iong about Ieaving...
没想到他真的走了
...I didn't think he'd really do it.
甘道夫？
Gandalf?
比尔博的戒指
Bilbo's ring.
他去和精灵住在一起
He's gone to stay with the EIves.
他把袋底洞留给你
He's Ieft you Bag End.
还有他所有的财产
AIong with all his possessions.
戒指现在是你的了
The ring is yours now.
把它放到看不到的地方
Put it somewhere out of sight.
你要去哪儿？
Where are you going?
有些事我一定要去处理
There are some things that I must see to.
什么事？
What things?
问题 需要解答的问题
Questions. Questions that need answering.
你才刚到
You've only just arrived.
我不明白
I don't understand.
我也不明白
Neither do I.
保守它的秘密
Keep it secret.
保证它的安全
Keep it safe.
夏尔！
Shire!
巴金斯！
Baggins!
第二纪元的3434年
"The year 3434 of the Second Age.
以下记载的是刚铎之王埃西铎...
Here follows the account of Isildur,High King of Gondor...
以及找到至尊魔戒的过程
...and the finding of the Ring of Power. "
它落到我手上了
"It has come to me.
这只至尊魔戒将是我的镇国之宝
The One Ring. It shall be an heirloom of my kingdom.
我的后代将永远对它效忠
All those who follow in my bloodline shall be bound to its fate...
我绝不容许魔戒受到任何损伤
...for I will risk no hurt to the Ring.
这是我的宝贝
It is precious to me...
我经过多少痛苦才得到它
... though I buy it with great pain.
戒指的刻痕逐渐消褪
The markings upon the band begin to fade.
那些赤焰般的文字现在全部消失
The writing,which at first was as clear as red flame,has all but disappeared.
只有火焰能让秘密显现
A secret now that only fire can tell. "
夏尔
Shire.
巴金斯
Baggins.
这周围没有巴金斯家族 他们都住在哈比屯
There's no Bagginses around here. They're all up in Hobbiton.
在那边
That way.
我的身心己疲惫
To heal my heart and drown my woe
阵阵风雨不停歇
Rain may fall and wind may blow
但是我仍有
But there still be
好长的路要走
Many miles to go
雨滴声音多美妙
Sweet is the sound of the pouring rain
大珠小珠落玉盘
And the stream that falls From hill to plain
不管硬水或清泉
Better than rain or rippling brook
都比不上这儿的啤酒
Is a mug of beer inside this Took
最近有一些陌生人经过夏尔
There's been some strange folk crossing the Shire.
包括矮人族和更可怕的坏人
Dwarves and others of a Iess than savory nature.
一场大战即将来临
War is brewing.
山里头来了一群妖魔鬼怪
The mountains are fair teeming with goblins.
这些只是谣传或是小孩子的童言童语而己
Far-off tales and children's stories,that's all that is.
你说话像老比尔博・巴金斯 疯疯癫癫的
You're beginning to sound Iike that old Bilbo Baggins. Cracked,he was.
佛罗多先生 他是有点疯癫
Young Mr. Frodo here,he's cracking.
还以它为荣
And proud of it.
干杯 老伯
Cheers,Gaffer.
干杯
Cheers.
夏尔以外的事跟我们无关
It's none of our concern what goes on beyond our borders.
只要你们不去惹麻烦 麻烦就不会找上门
Keep your nose out of trouble,and no trouble'll come to you.
晚安 小伙子们
Good night,lads.
晚安
Good night.
晚安了 可爱的金发姑娘
Good night,sweet maiden of the golden ale.
他最好别打她的主意
Mind who you're sweet-talking.
放心啦 山姆 萝西知道他是个混蛋
Don't worry,Sam. Rosie knows an idiot when she sees one.
真的吗？
Does she?
晚安 山姆
Good night,Sam.
晚安 佛罗多先生
Good night,Mister Frodo.
它隐秘吗？它安全吗？
Is it secret? Is it safe?
你在做什么？
What are you doing?
伸出手来 佛罗多
Hold out your hand,Frodo.
很凉
It's quite cool.
你能看到什么？
What can you see?
你看到什么吗？
Can you see anything?
没有
Nothing.
什么也没有
There's nothing.
等等
Wait.
上面有刻痕
There are markings.
好像是精灵文 我看不懂
It's some form of EIvish. I can't read it.
很少人能看得懂
There are few who can.
这是魔多的古文字 我在这里念不出来
The language is that of Mordor,which I will not utter here.
魔多！
Mordor!
用通用语 它说的是
In the common tongue,it says:
至尊戒 驭众戒
"One Ring to rule them all...
至尊戒 寻众戒
...One Ring to find them...
魔戒至尊引众戒
...One Ring to bring them all...
禁锢众戒黑暗中
...and in the darkness bind them."
这就是至尊魔戒
This is the One Ring...
黑暗魔君索伦用末日火山的烈焰铸成
...forged by the Dark Lord Sauron in the fires of Mount Doom.
埃西铎从索伦手中夺过来
Taken by Isildur from the hand of Sauron himself.
比尔博找到它
Bilbo found it.
在咕噜的洞穴中
In Gollum's cave.
是的
Yes.
六十年来 比尔博不动声色地持有至尊魔戒
For 60 years,the Ring lay quiet in Bilbo's keeping...
他因此而延长了寿命 延迟了老化
...prolonging his Iife,delaying old age.
但不再如此了 佛罗多 邪恶在魔多蠢蠢欲动
But no Ionger,Frodo. Evil is stirring in Mordor.
至尊魔戒被唤醒了
The Ring has awoken.
它听到主人的召唤
It's heard its master's call.
但是他已经被消灭了 索伦已经被消灭了
But he was destroyed. Sauron was destroyed.
不 佛罗多
No,Frodo.
索伦的灵魂还存活着
The spirit of Sauron endured.
他的生命和至尊魔戒紧紧相系 而至尊魔戒仍然幸存
His Iife force is bound to the Ring,and the Ring survived.
索伦已经回来了
Sauron has returned.
他的半兽人大军与日俱增
His Orcs have multiplied.
他在魔多也重建了要塞巴拉多
His fortress at Barad-dur is rebuilt in the land of Mordor.
索伦只要得到至尊魔戒就能让黑暗再度笼罩大地
Sauron needs only this Ring to cover all the lands in a second darkness.
他在搜寻它
He is seeking it.
全心全意 不择手段地搜寻
Seeking it. All his thought is bent on it.
同时至尊魔戒也渴望
For the Ring yearns above all else...
回到它主人的手中
...to return to the hand of its master.
他们本为一体
They are one...
至尊魔戒和黑暗魔君
...the Ring and the Dark Lord.
佛罗多
Frodo...
绝对不能让他找到至尊魔戒
...he must never find it.
好
All right.
我们把它放起来 藏着它 我们再也不提它
We put it away. We keep it hidden. We never speak of it again.
没人知道它在这儿 是吧？
No one knows it's here,do they?
是不是？甘道夫
Do they,Gandalf?
有一个人知道比尔博得到至尊魔戒
There is one other who knew that Bilbo had the Ring.
我到处找咕噜
I Iooked everywhere for the creature Gollum.
但是敌人先找到他
But the enemy found him first.
我不知道他被拷打了多久
I don't know how long they tortured him.
但是在可怕的哀嚎和呻吟声中 他们听出两个名字
But amidst the endless screams and inane babble,they discerned two words.'
夏尔！
Shire!
巴金斯！
Baggins!
夏尔
Shire.
巴金斯
Baggins.
他们会找到这里
But that would Iead them here!
什么人？
Who goes there?
你拿去 甘道夫！
Take it,Gandalf!
拿去！
Take it!
不 佛罗多
No,Frodo.
你一定要拿去！
You must take it!
你不能把魔戒交给我！
You cannot offer me this ring!
我要把它送给你！
I'm giving it to you!
别诱惑我 佛罗多！
Don't tempt me,Frodo!
我不敢拿
I dare not take it.
更不能保证它的安全
Not even to keep it safe.
你要了解 佛罗多
Understand,Frodo...
我只希望利用至尊魔戒行善事
...I would use this Ring from a desire to do good.
但是通过我 它将释放无法想像的邪恶力量
But through me,it would wield a power too great and terrible to imagine.
但是它不能留在夏尔！
But it cannot stay in the Shire!
没错
No.
的确不能
No,it can't.
我该怎么做？
What must I do?
你一定要离开 尽快离开
You must Ieave. And Ieave quickly.
哪里？我该去哪里？
Where? Where do I go?
离开夏尔 赶到布理村
Get out of the Shire. Make for the village of Bree.
布理
Bree.
那你呢？
What about you?
我会等你...
I'll be waiting for you...
在跃马旅店
...at the inn of the Prancing Pony.
魔戒在那儿安全吗？
And the Ring will be safe there?
我不知道 佛罗多
I don't know,Frodo.
我没有一点答案
I don't have any answers.
我必须去见巫师长 他有智慧和力量 相信我 佛罗多
I must see the head of my order. He is both wise and powerful. Trust me,Frodo.
他知道该怎么做
He'll know what to do.
你不能用巴金斯这名字
You'll have to Ieave the name of Baggins behind you.
这名字在夏尔之外不安全
That name is not safe outside the Shire.
白天赶路 别走大道
Travel only by day. And stay off the road.
我可以很容易穿过农田
I can cut across country easily enough.
我亲爱的佛罗多
My dear Frodo.
哈比人真不可思议
Hobbits really are amazing creatures.
你只要一个月就能了解他们
You can Iearn all that there is to know about their ways in a month.
然而一百年后
And yet,after a hundred years...
他们仍然让你吃惊不已
...they can still surprise you.
趴下去
Get down.
可恶的山姆卫斯・詹吉！你一直在偷听吗？
Confound it all,Samwise Gamgee! Have you been eavesdropping?
我才没有偷听 真的 我只是在窗外割草而已
I haven't been dropping no eaves. Honest. I was cutting the grass under the window.
你不认为现在剪草有点晚了？
A little late for trimming the verge,don't you think?
我听到说话声
I heard raised voices.
你听到什么？快说！
What did you hear? Speak!
没...没...没什么重要的
Nothing important.
我听到戒指 黑暗魔君和世界末日 但是...
That is,I heard a good deal about a ring,a Dark Lord and the end of the world but--
甘道夫先生 别伤害我 别把我变成怪物
PIease,Mr. Gandalf,sir,don't hurt me. Don't turn me into anything unnatural.
不要吗？
No?
也许不会
Perhaps not.
我想你有更好的用处
I've thought of a better use for you.
快点 山姆卫斯 跟上来
Come along,Samwise. Keep up.
你们两个要小心
Be careful,both of you.
敌人有很多眼线
The enemy has many spies in his service:
包括飞鸟野兽
Birds,beasts.
它安全吗？
Is it safe?
千万别戴上它
Never put it on...
黑暗魔君的爪牙会被它的力量吸引来
...for the agents of the Dark Lord will be drawn to its power.
你要记着 佛罗多...
AIways remember,Frodo...
至尊魔戒想要回到主人手上
...the Ring is trying to get back to its master.
它想要被找到
It wants to be found.
这就是了
This is it.
这是什么？
This is what?
我只要再跨一步
If I take one more step...
就是我离家最远的一次
...it'll be the farthest away from home I've ever been.
走吧 山姆
Come on,Sam.
我记得比尔博总是说
Remember what Bilbo used to say:
旅途很危险 佛罗多
"It's a dangerous business,Frodo."
一旦出了门 你踏步上了路
"Going out your door,You step onto the road.
如果你不继续前进
and if you don't keep your feet...
谁知道你可能跑到哪去了
... there's no knowing where you might be swept off to. "
星辰女王远在那西方之洋
a Galad ren
山姆
Sam.
光明普照
i veniar
木精灵
Wood-elves.
大地苍苍
hi' aladhremmin
吾等徜徉在林海莽莽
ennorath
他们要去白塔以外的港口
They're going to the harbor beyond the White Towers,
他们要去灰港岸
To the Grey Havens.
他们要离开中土世界
They're leaving Middle-earth.
永远不再回来
Never to return.
不知道为什么
I don't know why...
我会感到这么悲伤
...it makes me sad.
我躺到哪儿都有树根顶着我的背
Everywhere I lie there's a dirty great root sticking into my back.
闭上眼睛
Just shut your eyes...
想像着你躺在自己的床上
...and imagine you're back in your own bed...
柔软的床垫和舒服的羽毛枕头
...with a soft mattress and a Iovely feather pillow.
这没有用 佛罗多先生
It's not working,Mr. Frodo.
我在荒郊野外永远都睡不着
I'm never going to be able to sleep out here.
我也睡不着 山姆
Me neither,Sam.
末日火山升起硝烟
Smoke rises from the Mountain of Doom.
时间不多了
The hour grows late.
灰袍巫师甘道夫赶到艾辛格
And Gandalf the Grey rides to Isengard...
寻求我的建议
...seeking my counsel.
你就是为了这件事来找我？
For that is why you have come,is it not?
我的老朋友
My old friend.
萨鲁曼
Saruman.
你确信如此吗？
You are sure of this?
确信不疑
Beyond any doubt.
那么说至尊魔戒被发现了
So the Ring of Power has been found.
这么多年来 它一直在夏尔
All these Iong years,it was in the Shire.
就在我鼻子底下
Under my very nose.
而你却没有智慧看出它
Yet you did not have the wit to see it.
你喜欢的半身人的烟草很明显地熏坏了你的头脑
Your Iove of the halfling's Ieaf has clearly slowed your mind.
但是还有时间 有足够的时间对抗索伦 如果我们行动迅速
But we still have time. Time enough to counter Sauron if we act quickly.
时间？
Time?
我们哪来的时间？
What time do you think we have?
索伦的力量几乎完全恢复
Sauron has regained much of his former strength.
虽然他尚未完全复生
He cannot yet take physical form...
但他的灵魂仍有强大魔力
...but his spirit has Iost none of its potency.
虽然他被封在要塞中 但是他却无所不知
Concealed within his fortress,the Lord of Mordor sees all.
他的视线能穿透乌云 阴影 土地甚至肉体
His gaze pierces cloud,shadow,earth and flesh.
你知道我在说什么 甘道夫
You know of what I speak,Gandalf.
一个被烈焰包围的巨大眼晴
A Great Eye,Iidless,wreathed in flame.
索伦之眼
The Eye of Sauron.
他正在聚集邪恶力量
He is gathering all evil to him.
很快 他就能召集大军向中土世界展开攻击
Very soon,he'll have summoned an army great enough for an assault upon Middle-earth.
你知道这些？
You know this?
怎么会？
How?
我已经看到了
I have seen it.
真知晶球是个危险的东西 萨鲁曼
A palantir is a dangerous tool,Saruman.
为什么？
Why?
为什么我们要害怕使用它？
Why should we fear to use it?
其它的真知之石下落不明
They are not all accounted for,the lost Seeing-stones.
我们不知道有谁也在看
We do not know who else may be watching.
时间比你想的还迟
The hour is later than you think.
索伦已经在行动
Sauron's forces are already moving.
那九个已经离开米那斯魔窟
The Nine have Ieft Minas Morgul.
那九个？
The Nine?
他们在仲夏夜跨越艾辛河
They crossed the River Isen on Midsummer's Eve...
伪装成黑骑士
...disguised as riders in black.
他们已经到了夏尔？
They've reached the Shire?
他们会找到至尊魔戒
They will find the Ring.
然后杀死它的持有者
And kill the one who carries it.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
你不会真的以为哈比人能对抗索伦吧？
You did not seriously think that a Hobbit could contend with the will of Sauron?
谁都无法对抗他
There are none who can.
反抗魔多的力量...
Against the power of Mordor...
是毫无胜算的
...there can be no victory.
我们必须投靠他 甘道夫
We must join with him,Gandalf.
我们必须投靠索伦
We must join with Sauron.
这么做才聪明 我的朋友
It would be wise,my friend.
告诉我...
Tell me...
朋友...
...friend...
智者萨鲁曼几时发疯了？
...when did Saruman the Wise abandon reason for madness?
我给了你机会...
I gave you the chance...
自愿帮助我...
...of aiding me willingly...
但是你却选择了痛苦！
...but you have elected the way of pain!
佛罗多先生？
Mr. Frodo?
佛罗多？佛罗多！
Frodo? Frodo!
我以为把你跟丢了
I thought I'd lost you.
你在说什么？
What are you talking about?
甘道夫跟我说过
It's just something Gandalf said.
他说什么？
What did he say?
“紧跟着他 山姆卫斯・詹吉” 我会紧跟着你
"Don't you lose him,Samwise Gamgee." And I don't mean to.
山姆 我们还在夏尔 能有什么事？
Sam,we're still in the Shire. What could possibly happen?
佛罗多
Frodo.
梅里 是佛罗多・巴金斯
Merry,it's Frodo Baggins.
哈罗 佛罗多
Hello,Frodo.
快起来
Get off him.
起来 佛罗多
Come on,Frodo.
这是什么意思？
What's the meaning of this?
你们偷摘老农夫马嘎的菜！
You've been into Farmer Maggot's crop!
你们再敢回来！
You get back here!
快滚出我的菜地！
Get out of my field!
你们最好小心点别让我抓到！
You'll know the devil if I catch up with you!
我不知道他干嘛那么生气 只是两根胡萝卜
I don't know why he's so upset. It's only a couple of carrots.
还有几棵包心菜
And some cabbages.
和上礼拜我们挖的三袋马铃薯
And those three bags of potatoes that we lifted last week.
还有上上礼拜的蘑菇
And then the mushrooms the week before.
对 皮聘 重点是...
Yes,Pippin. My point is...
他太小题大作了
...he's clearly overreacting.
快跑！
Run!
好险啊
Oh,that was close.
我好像摔断了什么
I think I've broken something.
布兰迪巴克和图克家最会惹麻烦！
Trust a Brandybuck and a Took!
什么？那是一个便道 一条捷径呢
What? That was just a detour. A short cut.
去哪儿的捷径？
Short cut to what?
蘑菇！
Mushrooms!
那是我的
That's mine.
那个不错 梅里
That's nice,Merry.
这里也有一个不错的 山姆
Here's a nice one,Sam.
我们最好躲起来
I think we should get off the road.
躲起来！
Get off the road!
快点！
Quick!
别出声！
Be quiet!
那是什么东西？
What was that?
有什么东西吗？
Anything?
什么也没有
Nothing.
这是怎么回事？
What is going on?
黑骑士在找什么东西或是什么人
That Black Rider was looking for something. Or someone.
佛罗多？
Frodo?
趴下！
Get down!
我一定要离开夏尔
I have to leave the Shire.
山姆和我要赶到布理
Sam and I must get to Bree.
好
Right.
巴寇伯理渡口 跟我来
Bucklebury Ferry. Follow me.
快跑！
Run!
这儿！跟我来！
This way! Follow me!
快跑！
Run!
快去松绳 山姆！
Get the rope,Sam!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
快跑！佛罗多！
Run,Frodo!
快！快点！
Go! Hurry!
佛罗多 快跑！
Frodo,come on!
快！快点！跳！
Come on! Faster! Jump!
最近的渡桥有多远？
How far to the nearest crossing?
烈酒桥 二十里
The Brandywine Bridge. 20 miles.
来吧
Come on.
你们要干什么？
What do you want?
我们要去跃马旅店
We're heading for the Prancing Pony.
哈比人 四个哈比人！
Hobbits. Four Hobbits!
这么说 你们离开夏尔了 什么风把你们吹到布理的？
What's more,out of the Shire by your talk. What business brings you to Bree?
我们只是想住旅店
We wish to stay at the inn.
我们的事你管不着
Our business is our own.
好吧 年轻人 我不是想找事
All right,young sir. I meant no offense.
天黑后我就得多问一下
It's my job to ask questions after nightfall.
听说附近有怪人游荡
There's talk of strange folk abroad.
小心一点比较好
Can't be too careful.
让开！看好你的路
Out of the way! Watch where you're walking.
（跃马旅店）
打扰了
Excuse me.
晚上好 小客官 需要什么？
Good evening,little masters. What can I do for you?
如果你们想住一宿 我们有舒适的哈比人房间
If you're seeking accommodation,we got some cozy Hobbit-sized rooms available.
包君满意 请问大名是...
Always proud to cater to the Little Folk,Mister...?
山下 我叫山下
Underhill. My name's Underhill.
山下
Underhill,yes.
我们是灰袍巫师甘道夫的朋友
We're friends of Gandalf the Grey.
你能告诉他我们来了吗？
Can you tell him we've arrived?
甘道夫？
Gandalf?
甘道夫
Gandalf.
哦 对...
Oh,yes...
我想起来了 有点老
...I remember. Elderly chap.
长长的灰胡子 尖尖的帽子
Big grey beard,pointy hat.
半年没见到他了
Not seen him for six months.
我们现在怎么办？
What do we do now?
山姆
Sam...
他一定会来的
...he'll be here. He'll come.
别挡我的路！
Get out of my way!
那是什么？
What's that?
这个 我的朋友 是一品脱
This,my friend,is a pint.
这个是按品脱的？
It comes in pints?
我也要来一品脱
I'm getting one.
你已经喝了大半杯了！
You got a whole half already!
我们来了之后 那个人一直盯着你
That fellow's done nothing but stare at you since we arrived.
请问一下
Excuse me.
角落的那个人 他是谁？
That Man in the corner. Who is he?
他是一个游侠 他们很危险 成天在荒野游荡
He's one of them Rangers. They're dangerous folk,wandering the Wilds.
我不知道他的真名 但是这儿的人都叫他神行客
What his right name is,I've never heard,but around here he's known as Strider.
神行客
Strider.
巴金斯
Baggins.
巴金斯？当然 我认识一个
Baggins? Sure,I know a Baggins.
他就在那儿 佛罗多・巴金斯
He's over there. Frodo Baggins.
他是我二表弟 一次搬到他妈妈那边...
He's my second cousin,once removed on his mother's side...
而我三表弟 两次搬到...
...and my third cousin,twice removed....
皮聘！
Pippin!
慢点 佛罗多
Steady on,Frodo.
你躲不了的
You cannot hide.
我看得见你
I see you.
这里没有生命
There is no life...
在虚空中
...in the void.
只有...
Only...
死亡
...death.
你太惹人注意了 “山下先生”
You draw far too much attention to yourself,"Mr. Underhill."
你想要干什么？
What do you want?
我要你小心点 你戴的不是小玩意
A little more caution from you. That is no trinket you carry.
我什么也没戴
I carry nothing.
才怪
Indeed.
有必要我也能不被看到
I can avoid being seen if I wish...
但是完全消失可不是一件易事
...but to disappear entirely,that is a rare gift.
你是谁？
Who are you?
你害怕了？
Are you frightened?
是
Yes.
恐怕还不够 我知道谁在找你
Not nearly frightened enough. I know what hunts you.
放开他！否则我让你好看 长腿人
Let him go! Or I'll have you,Longshanks.
你很有胆量 小哈比人 但是这救不了你
You have a stout heart,little Hobbit. But that will not save you.
你不能再等巫师了 佛罗多
You can no longer wait for the wizard,Frodo.
他们来了
They're coming.
他们是什么东西？
What are they?
他们曾经是人类
They were once Men.
人类伟大的国王
Great kings of Men.
但是索伦给了他们九只魔戒
Then Sauron the Deceiver gave to them nine rings of power.
他们利欲熏心 毫不怀疑地收下
Blinded by their greed,they took them without question.
一个接一个 都沉沦于黑暗
One by one,falling into darkness.
现在他们是索伦的奴仆
Now they are slaves to his will.
他们是戒灵
They are the Nazg?l.
介于生与死之间
Ringwraiths. Neither living nor dead.
他们随时能感受到
At all times they feel...
魔戒的存在
... the presence of the Ring...
被至尊魔戒吸引着 他们会一直追杀你
...drawn to the power of the One. They will never stop hunting you.
你要带我们去哪儿?
Where are you taking us?
去荒野
Into the Wild.
我们怎么知道这个神行客是甘道夫的朋友？
How do we know this Strider is a friend of Gandalf?
我觉得敌人的爪牙会表面和善
I think a servant of the enemy would look fairer...
但内心凶恶
...and feel fouler.
他已经够凶恶了
He's foul enough.
我们除了相信他没有选择
We have no choice but to trust him.
他要带我们去哪里？
But where is he leading us?
瑞文戴尔 詹吉大师
To Rivendell,Master Gamgee.
去爱隆的家
To the house of Elrond.
你们听到了吗？瑞文戴尔
Did you hear that? Rivendell.
我们要去见精灵
We're going to see the Elves.
各位 天黑才能歇脚
Gentlemen,we do not stop till nightfall.
那早餐怎么办？
What about breakfast?
你们已经吃过了
You've already had it.
我们是吃过一顿
We've had one,yes.
那第二顿早餐呢？
What about second breakfast?
他不知道有第二顿早餐 皮聘
Don't think he knows about second breakfast,Pip.
那早午餐呢？午餐？下午茶？晚餐？宵夜？
What about elevenses? Luncheon? Afternoon tea? Dinner? Supper?
他应该知道吧
He knows about them,doesn't he?
我看不见得
I wouldn't count on it.
皮聘！
Pippin!
没有哈比人它们都吃些什么呢？
What do they eat when they can't get Hobbit?
蒂努薇尔美精灵
Tinúviel elvanui
独步群芳真智慧
Elleth alfirin ethelhael
轻丝如瀑洒贝伦
O hon ring finnil fuinui
玉臂轻摇闪银辉
A renc gelebrin thiliol
她是谁？
Who is she?
你歌中所唱的女子
This woman you sing of.
露西安
'Tis the lady of Lúthien.
一个爱上凡人贝伦的女精灵
The Elf-maiden who gave her love to Beren,a mortal.
她后来怎么了？
What happened to her?
她死了
She died.
快睡吧 佛罗多
Get some sleep,Frodo.
艾辛格听您的命令
The power of Isengard is at your command...
黑暗魔君索伦
... Sauron,Lord of the Earth.
替我召集一支魔多大军
Build me an army worthy of Mordor.
魔多有什么命令 主人？魔眼有什么吩咐？
What orders from Mordor,my lord? What does the Eye command?
我们有很多事要做
We have work to do.
这些树非常坚韧 主人 树根很深
The trees are strong,my lord. Their roots go deep.
把它们全都拉倒
Rip them all down.
这是风云顶t望台
This was the great watchtower of Amon Sul.
今晚在这里过夜
We shall rest here tonight.
这些给你们 一定要随身佩带
These are for you. Keep them close.
我到四周看一下
I'm going to have a look around.
别乱跑
Stay here.
我的蕃茄熟了
My tomato's burst.
我能来点熏肉吗？
Could I have some bacon?
吃蕃茄吗 山姆？
Want a tomato,Sam?
你们在干什么？！
What are you doing?!
烤蕃茄 香肠和熏肉
Tomatoes,sausages,nice crispy bacon.
我们给你留了一些 佛罗多先生
We saved some for you,Mr. Frodo.
快把火熄掉 笨蛋！快熄掉！
Put it out,you fools! Put it out!
这下可好了！蕃茄上都是灰！
That's nice! Ash on my tomatoes!
快走！
Go!
退后 你们这些恶魔！
Back,you devils!
- 在冰冷和黑暗中没有生命
- 这里只有死亡！
- Gu kibum kelkum-ishi,burzum-ishi.Akha - gum-ishi ashi gurum.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
山姆
Oh,Sam.
神行客！
Strider!
快救救他 神行客
Help him,Strider.
他被魔窟剑刺中了
He's been stabbed by a Morgul blade.
我救不了他 他需要精灵的医治
This is beyond my skill to heal. He needs Elvish medicine.
快点！
Hurry!
还有六天到瑞文戴尔！他撑不下去！
We're six days from Rivendell! He'll never make it!
坚持住 佛罗多
Hold on,Frodo.
甘道夫！
Gandalf!
你看 佛罗多 这就是比尔博先生说的巨魔
Look,Frodo. It's Mr. Bilbo's trolls.
佛罗多先生？他好冰冷
Mr. Frodo? He's going cold.
他会死吗？
Is he going to die?
他正在进入幽界 很快也会成为他们那样的亡灵
He's passing into the Shadow World. He'll soon become a Wraith like them.
他们就在附近
They're close.
山姆 你知道阿夕位斯草吗？
Sam,do you know the Athelas plant?
阿夕位斯？
Athelas?
又叫王之剑
Kingsfoil.
王之剑 对 是一种草药
Kingsfoil,aye,it's a weed.
它能减缓毒性发作 快去找！
It may help to slow the poisoning. Hurry!
怎么了？一个游侠竟然毫无防备？
What's this? A Ranger caught off his guard?
佛罗多
Frodo.
我是亚玟 我是来帮助你的
I'm Arwen. Telin le thaed
聆听我的呼唤...
Lasto beth n?n...
回到光明之处
Tolo dan na ngalad
她是谁？
Who is she?
佛罗多
Frodo.
她是个精灵
She's an Elf.
他越来越衰弱了
He's fading.
他撑不了多久
He's not going to last.
我们一定要带他去找我父亲
We must get him to my father.
我找了你两天
I've been looking for you for two days.
你要带他去哪儿？
Where are you taking him?
有五个戒灵在跟着你 我不知道另外四个在哪里
There are five Wraiths behind you. Where the other four are,I do not know.
陪着哈比人 我会给你们送马来
Dartho guin perian. Rych le ad tolthathon.
我骑马更快 我带他走
Hon mabathon. Rochon ellint im.
路上太危险了
Andelu i ven.
他们在说什么？
What are they saying?
佛罗多快死了 如果我能渡过河...
Frodo f?r. Ae athradon i hir
我族人的力量就能保护他
tur gwaith nin beriatha hon.
我不怕他们
I do not fear them.
那好吧
Be iest l?n.
亚玟
Arwen...
拼命骑 别回头
...ride hard. Don't look back.
飞奔吧 阿斯法洛斯 飞奔吧！
Noro lim,Asfaloth,noro lim!
你在干嘛？！那些戒灵就在附近！
What are you doing?! Those Wraiths are still out there!
飞奔吧 阿斯法洛斯！
Noro lim,Asfaloth!
把半身人交给我 女精灵
Give up the halfling,She-Elf.
如果你要他 过来求他啊
If you want him,come and claim him.
迷雾山脉的流水啊 聆听此圣言
Nin o Chithaeglir,lasto beth daer,
涨起河水向戒灵进攻！
Rimmo nin Bruinen,dan in Ulair!
不 不！
No. No!
佛罗多 不！
Frodo,no.
佛罗多 别放弃！
Frodo,don't give in.
现在不行
Not now.
给予我的恩赐
What grace is given me...
请传递给他
...let it pass to him.
让他免遭厄运
Let him be spared.
拯救他
Save him.
聆听我的呼唤
Lasto beth n?n.
回到光明之处
Tolo dan na ngalad.
我在哪里？
Where am l?
你在爱隆王的家中
You are in the house of Elrond.
现在是10月24日早上10点 如果你想知道
And it is 10:00 in the morning on October 24th,if you want to know.
甘道夫！
Gandalf!
是 我在这儿
Yes,I'm here.
你能在这里真是幸运
And you're lucky to be here too.
再过几小时你就没救了
A few more hours and you would have been beyond our aid.
不过你的生命力真是强 我亲爱的哈比人
But you have some strength in you,my dear Hobbit.
发生了什么事 甘道夫？
What happened,Gandalf?
你怎么没去找我们？
Why didn't you meet us?
对不起 佛罗多
I am sorry,Frodo.
我有事耽搁了
I was delayed.
你不能随便和我绝交
A friendship with Saruman is not lightly thrown aside.
别再抗拒了 没有用的
One ill turn deserves another. It is over.
拥抱魔戒...
Embrace the power of the Ring...
或者拥抱你自己的毁灭！
...or embrace your own destruction!
世上只有一个魔戒之王
There is only one Lord of the Ring.
只有他能够驾驭魔戒
Only one who can bend it to his will.
他不会和你分享权力
And he does not share power.
所以你选择了死亡
So you have chosen death.
甘道夫？怎么了？
Gandalf? What is it?
没什么 佛罗多
Nothing,Frodo.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
山姆
Sam.
老天保佑你终于醒了！
Bless you,you're awake!
山姆一直守在你身边
Sam has hardly left your side.
我们好担心你 对吧 甘道夫先生？
We were that worried about you. Weren't we,Mr. Gandalf?
幸好有爱隆王 你开始痊愈了
By the skills of Lord Elrond,you're beginning to mend.
欢迎光临瑞文戴尔 佛罗多・巴金斯
Welcome to Rivendell,Frodo Baggins.
比尔博！
Bilbo!
哈喽 佛罗多 我的孩子
Hello,Frodo,my lad.
比尔博
Bilbo.
去而复返...
"There and Back Again:
哈比人的故事 比尔博・巴金斯著
A Hobbit's Tale,by Bilbo Baggins."
太棒了
This is wonderful.
我很想再回去
I meant to go back...
我很想再去幽暗密林一趟
...wander the paths of Mirkwood...
探访长湖镇
...visit Lake-town...
再看一眼孤山
...see the Lonely Mountain again.
但是我终于年老力衰了
But age,it seems,has finally caught up with me.
（夏尔）
我想念夏尔
I miss the Shire.
我从小就幻想我能到别的地方
I spent all my childhood pretending I was off somewhere else.
跟你一起去冒险
Off with you,on one of your adventures.
但我自己的冒险却不是这么回事
But my own adventure turned out to be quite different.
我跟你不一样 比尔博
I'm not like you,Bilbo.
我亲爱的孩子
My dear boy.
我还忘了什么？
Now,what have I forgotten?
包裹好了？
Packed already?
做好准备总没什么坏处
No harm in being prepared.
你不是很想看看精灵吗 山姆？
I thought you wanted to see the Elves.
是啊
I do.
你想看得不得了
More than anything.
是啊
I did.
只是...
It's just....
我们照甘道夫说的做了 不是吗？
We did what Gandalf wanted,didn't we?
我们把魔戒带到瑞文戴尔 我觉得...
We got the Ring this far,to Rivendell. And I thought...
你的伤快好了 我们也该走了
...seeing as how you're on the mend,we'd be off soon.
回家
Off home.
你说的对 山姆
You are right,Sam.
我们完成了任务
We did what we set out to do.
魔戒在瑞文戴尔很安全
The Ring will be safe in Rivendell.
我也准备好回家了
I am ready to go home.
他的体力恢复了
His strength returns.
但他的伤永远无法痊愈 一辈子都会跟着他
That wound will never fully heal. He will carry it the rest of his life.
经过这一路的冒险
And yet to have come so far still bearing the Ring...
证明哈比人能抗拒魔戒的诱惑
...the Hobbit has shown extraordinary resilience to its evil.
他不该背负这个重担
It is a burden he should never have had to bear.
我们不能再要求佛罗多了
We can ask no more of Frodo.
甘道夫 敌人正在行动
Gandalf,the enemy is moving.
索伦大军在东方集结 他的邪跟正在盯着瑞文戴尔
Sauron's forces are massing in the East. His Eye is fixed on Rivendell.
还有萨鲁曼 你告诉我 也背叛了我们
And Saruman,you tell me,has betrayed us.
我们的盟友越来越少
Our list of allies grows thin.
他的变节比你知道的还要严重
His treachery runs deeper than you know.
通过邪恶的手段 他把半兽人和怪兽混在一起
By foul craft,Saruman has crossed Orcs with Goblin-men.
在艾辛格的洞窟中培育了一支军队
He's breeding an army in the caverns of lsengard.
一支能在白天出没的劲旅
An army that can move in sunlight and cover great distance at speed.
萨鲁曼要来抢夺至尊魔戒
Saruman is coming for the Ring.
精灵无法抵抗这股邪恶力量
This evil cannot be concealed by the power of the Elves.
我们没有力量对抗魔多和艾辛格！
We do not have the strength to fight both Mordor and lsengard!
甘道夫
Gandalf...
至尊魔戒不能留在这儿
...the Ring cannot stay here.
整个中土世界都受到威胁
This peril belongs to all Middle-earth.
他们必须决定如何拯救世界
They must decide now how to end it.
精灵的时代结束了 我的族人要离开这个海港
The time of the Elves is over. My people are leaving these shores.
我们走了你们要向谁求救？矮人族吗？
Who will you look to when we've gone? The Dwarves?
他们都躲在山洞挖宝藏 一点都不关心别人的问题
They hide in mountains seeking riches. They care not for the troubles of others.
我们要把希望放在人类身上
It is in Men that we must place our hope.
人类？
Men?
人类太脆弱了 他们的种族正在衰亡
Men are weak. The race of Men is failing.
登丹人的血液不再纯正 他们的骄傲和荣耀早被遗忘
The blood of Númenor is all but spent,its pride and dignity forgotten.
魔戒幸存都是因为人类
It is because of Men the Ring survives.
当时我也在场 甘道夫
I was there,Gandalf.
三千年前我也在场
I was there 3000 years ago...
埃西铎取走至尊魔戒
... when Isildur took the Ring.
人类堕落的那天我也在场
I was there the day the strength of Men failed.
埃西铎 快！跟我来
Isildur,hurry! Follow me.
我带埃西铎来到末日火山
I led Isildur into the heart of Mount Doom...
只有在那里才能摧毁至尊魔戒
... where the Ring was forged,the one place it could be destroyed.
把它丢进烈焰中！
Cast it into the fire!
毁了它！
Destroy it!
不
No.
埃西铎！
Isildur!
那天就该结束一切 但是邪恶却存活下去
It should have ended that day,but evil was allowed to endure.
埃西铎占有了至尊魔戒 皇室血脉就此断绝
Isildur kept the Ring. The line of kings is broken.
人类早已失去力量
There's no strength left in the world of Men.
他们群龙无首四处流窜
They're scattered,divided,leaderless.
还有一个人能让他们联合
There is one who could unite them.
有一个人能继承刚铎王位
One who could reclaim the throne of Gondor.
但他早已放弃王位了
He turned from that path a long time ago.
他选择自我放逐
He has chosen exile.
你不是精灵
You are no Elf.
我是南方来的人类
Men of the South are welcome here.
你是谁？
Who are you?
我是灰袍巫师甘道夫的朋友
I am a friend to Gandalf the Grey.
那我们来的目的一样
Then we are here on common purpose...
朋友
...friend.
纳希尔圣剑的碎片
The shards of Narsil.
这把利刃砍断索伦的手指
The blade that cut the Ring from Sauron's hand.
它还是很锋利
It's still sharp.
但也只是个残缺的宝物
But no more than a broken heirloom.
你为什么害怕过去？
Why do you fear the past?
你是埃西铎的后代 而不是埃西铎
You are lsildur's heir,not lsildur himself.
你不会重蹈他的覆辙
You are not bound to his fate.
我身上流着跟他一样的血
The same blood flows in my veins.
一样的软弱
The same weakness.
你的时代会来临的
Your time will come.
你会面对同样的邪恶 而你会击败它
You will face the same evil. And you will defeat it.
阴影还没有控制一切
A si i-Dhúath ú orthor,Aragorn.
没有笼罩你...没有笼罩我
ú or le a ú or nin.
你记得我们第一次见面吗？
Renech i lu i erui govannen?
我以为自己迷失在梦境中
Nauthannem i ned ol reniannen.
这么多年过去了
Gwenwin in enninath…
你那时没有现在的忧虑
U-arnech in naeth i si celich.
你还记得我说过什么吗？
Renech i beth i pennen?
你说你愿意跟我一起
You said you'd bind yourself to me...
放弃精灵的不朽生命
...forsaking the immortal life of your people.
我仍愿意这么做
And to that I hold.
我宁愿和你共度一生
I would rather share one lifetime with you...
也不愿面对永生不死的孤寂
...than face all the Ages of this world alone.
我选择凡人的生活
I choose a mortal life.
你不能给我这个
You cannot give me this.
这是我的选择
It is mine to give to whom I will...
如同我的心
...like my heart.
来自远方的陌生人和老朋友
Strangers from distant lands,friends of old...
你们要商议如何对抗魔多
...you've been summoned here to answer the threat of Mordor.
中土世界正面临灭亡的命运 无人能幸免
Middle-earth stands upon the brink of destruction. None can escape it.
你们不团结就会遭到灭亡
You will unite,or you will fall.
每一个种族都关系着这个灾难 这个厄运
Each race is bound to this fate,this one doom.
把魔戒拿来 佛罗多
Bring forth the Ring,Frodo.
这果然是真的
So it is true.
我曾经在梦中
In a dream...
看到东方的天空暗淡
...I saw the eastern sky grow dark...
但是西方却只有一线微光
...but in the West a pale light lingered.
有一个声音在呐喊
A voice was crying:
你即将面临灭亡的命运
"Your doom is near at hand.
埃西铎克星已被寻获
Isildur's Bane is found."
埃西铎克星
Isildur's Bane.
波罗莫！
Boromir!
至尊戒驭众戒
Ash nazg durbatul?k
至尊戒寻众戒
ash nazg gimbatul
至尊戒引众戒
ash nazg thrakatuluk
禁锢众戒黑暗中
agh burzum-ishi krimpatul.
从来没有人敢在这里说出魔多的邪恶魔音
Never before has any voice uttered the words of that tongue here in lmladris.
我并不想请求你的原谅 爱隆王
I do not ask your pardon,Master Elrond...
因为魔多的邪恶魔音
...for the Black Speech of Mordor...
也许很快就会
...may yet be heard...
响彻整个西方世界！
...in every corner of the West!
魔戒是一种邪恶力量
The Ring is altogether evil.
它是一个礼物
It is a gift.
一个对抗魔多的礼物
A gift to the foes of Mordor.
何不利用这只魔戒？
Why not use this Ring?
我父亲是刚铎的摄政王
Long has my father,the Steward of Gondor...
他一直奋力和魔多抗争 我们流着鲜血
...kept the forces of Mordor at bay. By the blood of our people...
保护你们的安全
...are your lands kept safe.
把敌人的武器交给刚铎 让我们利用它来对抗邪恶
Give Gondor the weapon of the enemy. Let us use it against him.
你无法使用它 我们谁都不能
You cannot wield it. None of us can.
至尊魔戒只听从索伦 它没有第二个主人
The One Ring answers to Sauron alone. It has no other master.
区区一个游侠懂什么？
And what would a Ranger know of this matter?
他不只是游侠
This is no mere Ranger.
他是阿拉贡 阿拉松之子
He is Aragorn,son of Arathorn.
你应该对他效忠
You owe him your allegiance.
阿拉贡
Aragorn.
你是埃西铎的后代？
This is lsildur's heir?
也是刚铎的王位继承人
And heir to the throne of Gondor.
坐下 勒苟拉斯
Havo dad,Legolas
刚铎没有国王
Gondor has no king.
刚铎也不需要国王
Gondor needs no king.
阿拉贡说得对 我们不能使用魔戒
Aragorn is right. We cannot use it.
你们只有一个选择
You have only one choice.
至尊魔戒一定要摧毁
The Ring must be destroyed.
那我们还等什么？
What are we waiting for?
魔戒不可能被毁掉 金雳 葛罗音之子...
The Ring cannot be destroyed,Gimli,son of Glóin...
用在场的任何武器
...by any craft that we here possess.
魔戒是末日火山的烈焰铸成
The Ring was made in the fires of Mount Doom.
也只有在那儿才能摧毁它
Only there can it be unmade.
一定要深入魔多
It must be taken deep into Mordor...
把魔戒丢进末日火山的烈焰中
...and cast back into the fiery chasm from whence it came.
你们中的一个
One of you...
必须去
...must do this.
一个人不可能就这样闯进魔多
One does not simply walk into Mordor.
黑门不光有半兽人看守
Its Black Gates are guarded by more than just Orcs.
还有永不松懈的邪恶力量
There is evil there that does not sleep.
索伦的邪眼更是虎视眈眈
The Great Eye is ever-watchful.
那是一片死寂的荒原
It is a barren wasteland...
布满烈焰 灰烬和尘埃
...riddled with fire,and ash and dust.
你呼吸的空气就是毒气
The very air you breathe is a poisonous fume.
就算有千军万马也办不到 这是不可能的
Not with 10,000 men could you do this. It is folly.
你没听到爱隆王说的话吗？一定要摧毁魔戒
Have you heard nothing Lord Elrond has said? The Ring must be destroyed.
我还以为你是那个救世主呢！
And I suppose you think you are the one to do it!
如果我们失败了怎么办？魔戒被索伦抢回去怎么办？
And if we fail,what then? What happens when Sauron takes back what is his?
我死也不容许魔戒落入精灵手中！
I will be dead before I see the Ring in the hands of an Elf!
绝不要相信精灵！
Never trust an Elf!
大家在这儿争吵不休 索伦的力量就会越来越强！
Do you not understand? While you bicker amongst yourselves,Sauron's power grows!
谁都逃脱不了！你们都会遭到毁灭！
None can escape it! You'll all be destroyed!
至尊戒驭众戒
Ash nazg durbatuluk!
至尊戒寻众戒
Ash nazg gimbatul!
我愿意去
I will take it.
我愿意把魔戒带到魔多
I will take the Ring to Mordor.
虽然...
Though...
我不认得路
...I do not know the way.
我愿意帮你承受这个重担 佛罗多・巴金斯
I will help you bear this burden,Frodo Baggins...
只要你在承受
...as long as it is yours to bear.
如果用我的性命能保护你
If by my life or death I can protect you...
我愿意
...I will.
我的剑会保护你
You have my sword.
还有我的弓箭
And you have my bow.
以及我的斧头
And my ax.
你背负着大家的命运 小家伙
You carry the fates of us all,little one.
如果这是大家真正的意愿
If this is indeed the will of the Council...
那么刚铎也会支持他
...then Gondor will see it done.
佛罗多先生没有我哪都不去
Frodo's not going anywhere without me.
没错 是很难拆散你们...
It is hardly possible to separate you...
连你没份参加的秘密会议你也来了
...even when he is summoned to a secret Council and you are not.
我们也来了！
We're coming too!
除非你把我们五花大绑送回家
You'll have to send us home tied up in a sack to stop us.
总之 你需要个聪明的人来完成这个...
Anyway,you need people of intelligence on this sort of...
任务
...mission.
冒险
Quest.
行动
Thing.
那你第一个就不合格
Well,that rules you out,Pip.
九名同伴
Nine companions.
就这样吧
So be it.
你们就是魔戒远征队
You shall be the Fellowship of the Ring.
太棒了！
Great!
我们要去哪儿？
Where are we going?
她希望保护她的孩子...
Anirne hene beriad i chên ?n.
她以为你在瑞文戴尔会很安全
Ned Imladris nauthant e le beriathar aen.
你母亲知道你这一生都会遭到追杀
In her heart,your mother knew you'd be hunted all your life.
你逃避不了这个命运
That you'd never escape your fate.
精灵可以重新铸造王者之剑...
The skill of the Elves can reforge the sword of kings...
但是只有你拥有使用它的力量
...but only you have the power to wield it.
我并不想拥有这个力量
I do not want that power.
我从来都不想
I have never wanted it.
你是唯一的皇族继承人 没有别人
You are the last of that bloodline. There is no other.
我的宝剑！刺针
My old sword! Sting.
来 拿去 拿去
Here,take it. Take it.
好轻啊
It's so light.
没错 精灵打造的
Yes. Made by the Elves,you know.
半兽人接近剑身就会变蓝
The blade glows blue when Orcs are close.
那个时候 我的孩子 你就要格外小心
And it's times like that,my lad,when you have to be extra careful.
还有个漂亮的东西
Here's a pretty thing.
秘银
Mithril.
轻若鸿毛 韧如龙鳞
As light as a feather,and as hard as dragon scales.
让我看你把它穿上 快点
Let me see you put it on. Come on.
我的老戒指
My old ring.
我真的很想...
I should very much like...
再把它握在手中 最后一次
...to hold it again,one last time.
我很抱歉给你带来这些 我的孩子
I'm sorry I brought this upon you,my boy.
我很抱歉让你背负这个重担
I'm sorry that you must carry this burden.
我对这一切都很抱歉
I'm sorry for everything.
魔戒持有者要开始末日火山的征途
The Ring-bearer is setting out on the Quest of Mount Doom.
你们这些随行的伙伴没有许下誓言...
On you who travel with him,no oath...
也没有受到约束规定你们一定要走完全程
...nor bond is laid to go further than you will.
再会了 坚守你们的目的
Farewell. Hold to your purpose.
愿精灵 人类以及所有的自由之士的...
May the blessings of Elves and Men...
祝福伴随你们
...and all Free Folk go with you.
远征队等候魔戒持有者
The Fellowship awaits the Ring-bearer.
甘道夫 魔多是往左还是往右？
Mordor,Gandalf,is it left or right?
左
Left.
我们必须向迷雾山脉以西走四十天
We must hold to this course,west of the Misty Mountains,for 40 days.
幸运的话就能赶到洛汗隘口
If our luck holds,the Gap of Rohan will still be open to us.
从那儿往东走到魔多
From there,our road turns east to Mordor.
二 一 五 好！非常好！
Two,one,five. Good! Very good.
移动脚步
Move your feet.
你好帅哦 皮聘
You look good,Pippin.
谢了
Thanks.
快一点！
Faster!
虽然你们都不问我的意见...
If anyone was to ask for my opinion,which I note they're not...
我还是要说我们在绕远路
...I'd say we were taking the long way 'round.
甘道夫 我们大可以穿过摩瑞亚矿坑
Gandalf,we could pass through the Mines of Moria.
我表哥巴林会热烈地欢迎我们
My cousin Balin would give us a royal welcome.
不行 金雳 别无选择才能走摩瑞亚矿坑
No,I would not take the road through Moria unless I had no other choice.
对不起！
Sorry!
抓住他！
Get him!
夏尔万岁！
For the Shire!
压住他 把他压住 梅里！
Hold him. Hold him down,Merry!
先生们 够了
Gentlemen,that's enough.
你抓住我胳膊了！
You've got my arm! You've got my arm!
那是什么？
What is that?
没什么 只是一朵乌云
Nothing. It's just a wisp of cloud.
它移动得这么快
It's moving fast.
还迎着风
Against the wind.
登兰德的乌鸦！
Crebain from Dunland!
躲起来！
Hide!
快点！
Hurry!
隐蔽起来！
Take cover!
萨鲁曼的眼线
Spies of Saruman.
南方的路受到监视
The passage south is being watched.
我们一定要攀越卡兰拉斯山
We must take the Pass of Caradhras.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
波罗莫
Boromir.
我们受尽了恐惧和疑虑的折磨...
It is a strange fate that we should suffer so much fear and doubt...
就为了这小玩意
...over so small a thing.
这小小的玩意
Such a little thing.
波罗莫！
Boromir!
把魔戒还给佛罗多
Give the Ring to Frodo.
如你所愿
As you wish.
我才不要它
I care not.
甘道夫 你想带他们攀越卡兰拉斯山
So,Gandalf,you try to lead them over Caradhras.
要是失败 你能到哪儿？
And if that fails,where then will you go?
要是你被高山打败...
If the mountain defeats you...
你肯冒险走更危险的路吗？
... will you risk a more dangerous road?
醒来吧 残暴的红角峰！让你的尖角沾满血污！
Cuiva nwalca Carnirasse!Nai yarvaxea rasselya!
一股邪音从天而降
There is a fell voice on the air.
那是萨鲁曼！
It's Saruman!
他想制造雪崩！甘道夫 我们一定要回头！
He's trying to bring down the mountain! Gandalf,we must turn back!
不行！
No!
沉睡吧 卡兰拉斯！安静吧 沉睡吧！控制你的愤怒！
Losto Caradhras,sedho,hodo,nuitho i 'ruith!
醒来吧 残暴的红角峰！
Cuiva nwalca Carnirasse!
让你那沾满血污的尖角落到敌人头上！
Nai yarvaxea rasselya taltuva notto-carinnar!
我们一定要离开山岭！
We must get off the mountain!
赶到洛汗隘口 从西谷到我的城市！
Make for the Gap of Rohan,and take the west road to my city!
洛汗隘口离艾辛格太近了！
The Gap of Rohan takes us too close to lsengard!
上面走不成就走下面吧
We cannot pass over a mountain. Let us go under it.
让我们穿过摩瑞亚矿坑
Let us go through the Mines of Moria.
摩瑞亚 你很怕穿过矿坑
Moria. You fear to go into those mines.
矮人太贪心 挖得太深
The Dwarves delved too greedily and too deep.
你知道他们在西泽督姆的黑暗中唤醒了什么
You know what they awoke in the darkness of Khazad-d?m:
邪恶的炎魔
Shadow and flame.
让魔戒持有者决定
Let the Ring-bearer decide.
我们不能待在这儿！
We cannot stay here!
我们留下来就死定了
This will be the death of the Hobbits.
佛罗多？
Frodo?
我们走矿坑吧
We will go through the mines.
就这么办吧
So be it.
佛罗多 过来扶扶我这老头儿
Frodo,come and help an old man.
你的肩伤还好吧？
How is your shoulder?
好点了
Better than it was.
魔戒呢？
And the Ring?
你感觉到它的力量越来越大 对吧？
You feel its power growing,don't you?
我也感觉到了 你千万要小心
I've felt it too. You must be careful now.
邪恶力量不但会来自外面
Evil will be drawn to you from outside the Fellowship.
恐怕也会来自远征队员
And,I fear,from within.
那我该相信谁？
Who then do I trust?
你要相信你自己
You must trust yourself.
相信自己的力量
Trust your own strengths.
什么意思？
What do you mean?
这世上有很多力量...
There are many powers in this world...
正义的或邪恶的
...for good or for evil.
有些力量比我更强大
Some are greater than I am.
有些力量连我都没有遇见过
And against some I have not yet been tested.
摩瑞亚矿坑的...
The walls...
墙
...of Moria.
矮人的门关起来时是看不到的
Dwarf doors are invisible when closed.
没错 金雳  如果秘密被遗忘 连它们的主人都找不到
Yes,Gimli,their own masters cannot find them if their secrets are forgotten.
为什么我一点都不吃惊？
Why doesn't that surprise me?
让我看看
Well,let's see.
伊希尔丁金属
Ithildin.
它只会反射星光和月光
It mirrors only starlight and moonlight.
上面写着：都灵之门 摩瑞亚之主
It reads,"The Doors of Durin,Lord of Moria.
开口说 朋友 然后进入
Speak,friend,and enter.
那你认为是什么意思？
What do you suppose that means?
很简单 如果你是朋友 说出暗语门就开了
It's simple. If you are a friend,you speak the password and the doors will open.
精灵的大门 现在为我打开！
Annon Edhellen edro hi ammen!
矮人的门户 听从我的命令！
Fennas Nogothrim lasto beth lammen!
没有反应
Nothing's happening.
我以前知道所有精灵...
I once knew every spell in all the tongues of Elves...
人类和半兽人的语言
...Men and Orcs.
那你打算怎么办？
What are you going to do,then?
用你的头把大门撞开 皮里格林・图克！
Knock your head against these doors,Peregrin Took!
要是那样还撞不开...
And if that does not shatter them...
那就让我安静一下 别再问愚蠢的问题...
...and I am allowed a little peace from foolish questions...
我会努力找到打开的暗语
...I will try to find the opening words.
精灵的大门听从我的命令 矮人的入口...
Ando Eldarinwa… a lasta quettanya,Fenda Casarinwa…
矿坑不是一匹小马待的地方
Mines are no place for a pony.
即使它很勇敢也不行
Even one so brave as Bill.
再见了 比尔
Bye-bye,Bill.
去吧 比尔 去吧
Go on,Bill. Go on.
别担心 山姆 它认得回家的路
Don't worry,Sam,he knows the way home.
别玩水
Do not disturb the water.
没有用
Oh,it's useless.
这是一个谜语
It's a riddle.
开口说“朋友” 然后进入
Speak 'friend' and enter.
“朋友”用精灵语怎么说？
What's the Elvish word for "friend"?
朋友
Mellon.
很快 精灵大人 你就会见到矮人族的热情
Soon,Master Elf,you will enjoy the fabled hospitality of the Dwarves.
熊熊的火焰 清凉的啤酒和大块的烤肉！
Roaring fires,malt beer,ripe meat off the bone!
这个 我的朋友 就是我表哥巴林的家
This,my friend,is the home of my cousin Balin.
他们叫它矿坑
And they call it a mine.
矿坑！
A mine!
这不是矿坑 这是坟墓
This is no mine. It's a tomb.
不...
No....
不！
No!
半兽人
Goblins.
我们应该去洛汗隘口 我们就不应该来这儿
We make for the Gap of Rohan. We should never have come here.
快 从这里出去 出去！
Now,get out of here. Get out!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
救命！
Help!
神行客！
Strider!
救他！
Help!
放开他！
Get off him!
阿拉贡！
Aragorn!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
快进矿坑！
Into the mines!
勒苟拉斯！
Legolas!
快进山洞！
Into the cave!
快跑！
Run!
我们现在只有一个选择
We now have but one choice.
我们一定要穿过黑暗的矿坑
We must face the long dark of Moria.
保持警惕
Be on your guard.
有比半兽人更古老 更邪恶的东西...
There are older and fouler things than Orcs...
在这个黑暗的地底世界
...in the deep places of the world.
安静 要走四天才能到另一边
Quietly now. It's a four-day journey to the other side.
希望我们不会惊动什么
Let us hope that our presence may go unnoticed.
摩瑞亚矿坑最珍贵的不是黄金...
The wealth of Moria was not in gold...
或是珠宝...
...or jewels...
而是秘银
...but mithril.
比尔博有一件索林给的秘银打造的锁甲
Bilbo had a shirt of mithril rings that Thorin gave him.
简直是给国王的礼物
Oh,that was a kingly gift.
没错
Yes.
我从来没跟他说过...
I never told him...
那件秘银远比整个夏尔更值钱
...but its worth was greater than the value of the Shire.
皮聘
Pippin.
我不记得这地方
I have no memory of this place.
我们迷路了吗？
Are we lost?
没有
No.
我认为我们迷路了
I think we are.
甘道夫正在想
Gandalf's thinking.
梅里？
Merry?
干嘛？
What?
我饿了
I'm hungry.
下面有什么东西
There's something down there.
那是咕噜
It's Gollum.
咕噜？
Gollum?
他已经跟了我们三天
He's been following us for three days.
他从巴拉多的地牢逃出来
He escaped the dungeons of Barad-d?r?
逃出来...
Escaped...
或是被放出来
...or was set loose.
现在魔戒把他带到这儿来
Now the Ring has brought him here.
他对魔戒永远充满渴望
He will never be rid of his need for it.
他对至尊魔戒又爱又恨 就像他对自己爱恨交加
He hates and loves the Ring,as he hates and loves himself.
史麦戈的遭遇很悲惨
Sméagol's life is a sad story.
史麦戈是他的本名 在魔戒找到他之前
Yes,Sméagol he was once called. Before the Ring found him.
在魔戒让他发疯之前
Before it drove him mad.
真可惜比尔博当时没杀了他
It's a pity Bilbo didn't kill him when he had the chance.
可惜？
Pity?
比尔博同情他才没杀他
It is pity that stayed Bilbo's hand.
有很多活人本来就该死 也有些死人本来命不该绝
Many that live deserve death. Some that die deserve life.
你能安排他们的命运吗 佛罗多？
Can you give it to them,Frodo?
千万别轻易断定别人的生死
Do not be too eager to deal out death and judgment.
就连智者都无法决定命运
Even the very wise cannot see all ends.
我认为咕噜会跟这趟冒险有关 不管是好是坏...
My heart tells me that Gollum has some part to play yet,for good or ill...
在一切结束前
...before this is over.
比尔博的同情可能会决定很多人的命运
The pity of Bilbo may rule the fate of many.
我真希望魔戒没在我手中
I wish the Ring had never come to me.
真希望这一切都没发生
I wish none of this had happened.
每个人遇到难关都会这么想...
So do all who live to see such times.
但是那不由我们决定
But that is not for them to decide.
我们所能决定的是...
All we have to decide is...
在给予我们的时间内去做什么
what to do with the time that is given to us.
世上除了邪恶还有别的力量
There are other forces at work in this world,Frodo,besides the will of evil.
比尔博注定要找到魔戒
Bilbo was meant to find the Ring.
你也注定要得到它
In which case,you also were meant to have it.
能这么想就好了
And that is an encouraging thought.
是那条路
It's that way.
他记起来了
He's remembered.
不是
No.
但是这儿的空气闻起来没那么糟
But the air doesn't smell so foul down here.
如果拿不准 梅里・雅达克 那就跟着你的鼻子
If in doubt,Meriadoc,always follow your nose.
让我冒险再弄亮一点
Let me risk a little more light.
看吧...
Behold...
矮人族的宏伟领域和地下城市
...the great realm and Dwarf-city of Dwarrowdelf.
这真是令人大开眼界
There's an eye opener,and no mistake.
金雳！
Gimli!
不！
No!
不...
Oh,no.
不
No.
巴林长眠于此...
"Here lies Balin...
方丁之子...
...son of Fundin...
摩瑞亚之主
...Lord of Moria."
他死了
He is dead,then.
这就是我所担心的
It's as I feared.
我们必须离开 我们不能逗留
We must move on. We cannot linger.
他们攻下桥梁和第二大厅
"They have taken the bridge and the second hall.
我们闩住大门...
We have barred the gates...
但阻挡不了他们多久
...but cannot hold them for long.
大地在撼动
The ground shakes.
鼓声...
Drums...
鼓声从深处传来
...drums in the deep.
我们逃不出去
We cannot get out.
一个阴影在黑暗中移动
A Shadow moves in the dark.
我们逃不出去
We cannot get out.
他们来了
They are coming."
愚蠢的图克！
Fool of a Took!
下次把你也扔进去 免得你的愚蠢害了我们
Throw yourself in next time,and rid us of your stupidity.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
半兽人
Orcs.
退后！紧挨着甘道夫！
Get back! Stay close to Gandalf!
有一只巨魔
They have a cave-troll.
让它们来吧！
Let them come!
摩瑞亚有一个矮人还喘着气呢
There is one Dwarf yet in Moria who still draws breath.
我想我要为这个被绞死
I think I'm getting the hang of this.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
阿拉贡！阿拉贡！
Aragorn! Aragorn!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
不
Oh, no.
他还活着
He's alive.
我没事 我没受伤
I'm all right. I'm not hurt.
你应该没命的
You should be dead.
那一剑连野猪都能刺死
That spear would have skewered a wild boar.
小哈比人远比我们想像的厉害
I think there's more to this Hobbit than meets the eye.
秘银
Mithril.
你总是叫人吃惊 巴金斯先生
You are full of surprises, Master Baggins.
快到凯萨督姆桥！
To the Bridge of Khazad-d?m!
这边！
This way!
又来了什么怪物？
What is this new devilry?
炎魔
A Balrog.
远古的恶魔
A demon of the ancient world.
你们都不是它的对手
This foe is beyond any of you.
快跑！
Run!
快点！
Quickly!
甘道夫
Gandalf.
带领他们 阿拉贡
Lead them on, Aragorn.
桥就快到了
The bridge is near.
照我说的做！剑是无法对付炎魔的
Do as I say! Swords are no more use here.
甘道夫！
Gandalf!
梅里！皮聘！
Merry! Pippin!
山姆！
Sam!
谁也不能丢矮人
Nobody tosses a Dwarf.
别扯我的胡子！
Not the beard!
稳住
Steady.
站好！
Hold on!
稳住！
Hang on!
往前倾！
Lean forward!
稳住
Steady.
快点！
Come on!
快跳！
Now!
快过桥！
Over the bridge!
快过去！
Fly!
你不能过去！
You cannot pass!
甘道夫！
Gandalf!
我是圣火的仆人 高举着亚尔诺炽焰
I am a servant of the Secret Fire, wielder of the flame of Anor.
邪恶之火不会帮你 乌顿之火！
The dark fire will not avail you, flame of Udun!
滚回黑暗中吧
Go back to the Shadow.
你不能过去！
You shall not pass!
不！不！
No! No!
甘道夫！
Gandalf!
快走啊 你这傻瓜！
Fly, you fools!
不！
No!
阿拉贡！
Aragorn!
勒苟拉斯 把他们扶起来
Legolas, get them up.
让他们静一静吧！
Give them a moment, for pity's sake!
天一黑半兽人就会蜂拥而上
By nightfall, these hills will be swarming with Orcs.
我们一定要赶到罗斯洛立安森林
We must reach the woods of Lothlórien.
走吧 波罗莫 勒苟拉斯 金雳 把他们扶起来
Come, Boromir. Legolas. Gimli, get them up.
起来 山姆
On your feet, Sam.
佛罗多？
Frodo?
佛罗多！
Frodo!
跟紧了 小哈比人！
Stay close, young Hobbits!
听说一个大女巫住在这个树林
They say that a great sorceress lives in these woods.
一个精灵巫师...
An Elf-witch...
拥有可怕的法力
...of terrible power.
只要看她一眼...
All who look upon her...
就会被她的符咒击倒
...fall under her spell.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
然后永远消失
And are never seen again.
你的到来就像毁灭的脚步
Your coming to us is as the footsteps of doom.
你带来了巨大的邪恶 魔戒持有者
You bring great evil here, Ring-bearer.
佛罗多先生？
Mr. Frodo?
我这个矮人可不会被她轻易迷惑
Well, here's one Dwarf she won't ensnare so easily.
我有老鹰的锐眼和狐狸的耳朵
I have the eyes of a hawk and the ears of a fox.
这矮人喘气声这么大 就算在黑暗中也能射死他
The Dwarf breathes so loud, we could have shot him in the dark.
欢迎 勒苟拉斯 瑟兰督伊之子
Mae govannen,Legolas Thranduilion.
我们的远征队寻求你的帮忙 罗瑞安的哈尔达
Govannas vin gwennen le,Haldir o Lórien.
登丹人阿拉贡...
A Aragorn in Dúnedain
我们久仰你的大名
istannen le ammen
哈尔达
Haldir.
精灵真如传说中的有礼貌！
So much for the legendary courtesy of the Elves!
说我们都听得懂的话！
Speak words we can all understand!
自从黑暗时期我们就没跟矮人打过交道
We have not had dealings with the Dwarves since the Dark Days.
那你知道这些矮人会怎么说吗？
And you know what this Dwarf says to that?
我唾弃你的坟墓！
Ishkhaqwi ai durugnul!
那样很没有礼貌
That was not so courteous.
你带来了强大的邪恶力量
You bring great evil with you.
你们不能再前进了
You can go no further.
甘道夫不是白白牺牲
Gandalf's death was not in vain.
他也不会让你放弃希望
Nor would he have you give up hope.
你背负着沉重的担子 佛罗多
You carry a heavy burden, Frodo.
别再背负死亡的重担
Don't carry the weight of the dead.
你们跟我来
You will follow me.
卡拉斯加位顿
Caras Galadhon.
世界上精灵王国的中心
The heart of Elvendom on earth.
凯勒布理安王以及光明女王凯兰崔尔的国度
Realm of the Lord Celeborn and of Galadriel, Lady of Light.
敌人知道你们来到这里
The enemy knows you have entered here.
你们已经暴露了行踪
What hope you had in secrecy is now gone.
这儿只有八个人 但有九个人从瑞文戴尔出发
Eight there are here, yet nine there were set out from Rivendell.
告诉我 甘道夫呢？
Tell me, where is Gandalf?
我很想跟他说话
For I much desire to speak with him.
我很久没见过他了
I can no longer see him from afar.
灰袍巫师甘道夫并没有进入黄金森林
Gandalf the Grey did not pass the borders of this land.
他已坠入黑暗深渊
He has fallen into Shadow.
他被烈焰和黑暗吞噬
He was taken by both Shadow and flame.
魔苟斯的炎魔
A Balrog of Morgoth.
我们不小心进入摩瑞亚的陷阱
For we went needlessly into the net of Moria.
甘道夫做事一向都很小心
Needless were none of the deeds of Gandalf in life.
我们还不知道他的意图
We do not yet know his full purpose.
别让凯萨督姆的毁灭让你灰心丧志...
Do not let the great emptiness of Khazad-d?m fill your heart...
金雳 葛罗音之子
...Gimli, son of Glóin.
世上到处充满危险...
For the world has grown full of peril...
在所有的土地上...
...and in all lands...
爱都混合了悲伤
...Iove is now mingled with grief.
现在魔戒远征队会怎么样？
What now becomes of this Fellowship?
没有了甘道夫 希望也失去了
Without Gandalf, hope is lost.
这趟旅程险象环生
The quest stands upon the edge of a knife.
只要一不小心你们就会失败...
Stray but a little and it will fail...
世界末日也会降临
...to the ruin of all.
只要你们团结一致就有希望
Yet hope remains while the Company is true.
不要让你们的内心烦扰 快去休息吧...
Do not let your hearts be troubled. Go now and rest...
你们有太多的哀伤和疲惫
...for you are weary with sorrow and much toil.
今晚你们要好好睡一觉
Tonight, you will sleep....
欢迎 夏尔的佛罗多...
Welcome, Frodo of the Shire...
只有你见过邪眼！
...one who has seen the Eye!
欧络因(甘道夫)曾被西方众神派来守护东方的土地
A Olórin i yaresse Mentaner i Numeherui Tírien i Rómenóri
我们对这片土地的爱比深海还深
Melme nóren sina núra ala E?ro
悼念甘道夫的挽歌
A lament for Gandalf.
最贤明的迈雅 是什么让你离开了你热爱的土地
Maiaron i Oiosaila, Manan elye etevanne Nórie i malanelye?
他们说些什么？
What do they say about him?
我不忍心告诉你们
I have not the heart to tell you.
因为我的伤痛还未平息
For me, the grief is still too near.
我们宁愿抛弃一切选择屈服来挽留你
Ilfirin nairelma ullume nucuvalme. Nauva i nauva.
我打赌他们没有提到他放的烟火
I bet they don't mention his fireworks.
他们应该作诗来歌颂这一点
There should be a verse about them.
从古到今最棒的烟火
The finest rockets ever seen
在空中闪烁就像耀眼的星斗
They burst in stars of blue and green
这些闪闪发光的烟火
Or after thunder,
就像银河一样从天而降
silver showers
就跟天空飘下的花雨一样缤纷
Came falling like a rain of flowers
这都不足以形容它们有多壮观
Oh, that doesn't do them justice by a long road.
快休息吧
Take some rest.
这里很安全
These borders are well-protected.
我在这里无法休息
I will find no rest here.
我在头脑里听到她的声音
I heard her voice inside my head.
她提到我父亲和刚铎的灭亡
She spoke of my father and the fall of Gondor.
她对我说 即使现在仍有一线希望
She said to me, "Even now there is hope left."
但是我却看不到
But I cannot see it.
很久以来我们都没有希望
It is long since we had any hope.
我父亲是个高贵的人
My father is a noble man.
但是他的统治正在衰败...
But his rule is failing...
我们的子民也失去信心
...and our people lose faith.
他指望我能成功 我也想
He looks to me to make things right, and I would do it.
我想看到刚铎的荣耀恢复
I would see the glory of Gondor restored.
你以前见过吗 阿拉贡？
Have you ever seen it, Aragorn?
爱克西里昂的白塔
The White Tower of Ecthelion.
就像一串珍珠一样微微发光
Glimmering like a spike of pearl and silver.
塔上的旗帜随早晨的微风高高飘扬
Its banners caught high in the morning breeze.
你以前有没有...
Have you ever been called home...
被清晰的银号角声召唤回家？
...by the clear ringing of silver trumpets?
我见过那个白色城市...
I have seen the White City...
很久以前
...Iong ago.
有一天 我们将一起去那儿
One day, our paths will lead us there.
到时候塔上守卫将高喊
And the tower guard shall take up the call:
刚铎之王回来了
"The Lords of Gondor have returned."
你能看看镜子吗？
Will you look into the mirror?
我会看到什么？
What will I see?
就连最聪明的智者也不知道
Even the wisest cannot tell.
因为镜子...
For the mirror...
能显现很多事情
...shows many things.
过去的事情...
Things that were...
现在的事情...
...things that are...
还有一些事情...
...and some things...
尚未发生
...that have not yet come to pass.
我知道你看到什么
I knowwhat it is you saw.
因为它一样也在我心里呈现
For it is also in my mind.
如果你失败就会发生这些事
It is what will come to pass if you should fail.
远征队已经开始四分五裂
The Fellowship is breaking. It is already begun.
他会试图抢走魔戒
He will try to take the Ring.
你知道我说的是谁
You know of whom I speak.
他们会一个接一个被魔戒击垮
One by one, it will destroy them all.
只要你开口...
If you ask it of me...
我就把至尊魔戒给你
... I will give you the One Ring.
你肯毫无条件地给我
You offer it to me freely.
我承认我很渴望魔戒
I do not deny that my heart has greatly desired this.
我将成为魔戒之后
In place of a Dark Lord, you would have a queen...
她并不黑暗而是美丽得跟曙光一样耀眼！
...not dark but beautiful, and terrible as the dawn!
跟海洋一样高深莫测！
Treacherous as the sea!
远比土地更加坚强！
Stronger than the foundations of the earth!
世人都将迷恋我...
All shall love me...
而且自暴自弃
...and despair.
我通过了考验
I pass the test. I will diminish...
我将退隐到西方...
...and go into the West...
继续当凯兰崔尔女王
...and remain Galadriel.
我一个人无法摧毁它
I cannot do this alone.
你是魔戒持有者 佛罗多 持有至尊魔戒...
You are a Ring-bearer, Frodo. To bear a Ring of Power...
注定孤单一人
...is to be alone.
这是南雅 钻石之戒
This is Nenya, the Ring of Adamant.
我是它的守护者
And I am its keeper.
这个任务指派给你
This task was appointed to you.
如果你办不到...
And if you do not find a way...
没有人可以
...no one will.
我知道该怎么做了
Then I know what I must do.
只是...
It's just...
我感到害怕
...I'm afraid to do it.
即使再渺小的人也能改变未来
Even the smallest person can change the course of the future.
你知道半兽人是怎么来的吗？
Do you know how the Orcs first came into being?
它们曾经是精灵
They were Elves once.
但是却被黑暗力量...
Taken by the Dark Powers...
折磨到不成人形
...tortured and mutilated.
它们是被扭曲的可怕生物
A ruined and terrible form of life.
而现在...
And now...
变得完美
...perfected.
我的强兽人战士...
My fighting Uruk-hai...
你的主人是谁？
...whom do you serve?
萨鲁曼！
Saruman!
猎杀他们 找不到绝不罢手
Hunt them down. Do not stop until they are found.
你们没有痛苦 你们没有恐惧
You do not know pain. You do not know fear.
你们只会杀人！
You will taste Man-flesh!
有一个半身人手中有宝物
One of the halflings carries something of great value.
我要你毫发无伤地活抓他们
Bring them to me alive and unspoiled.
杀了其他人
Kill the others.
我们从来没有让外人穿上我们精灵的装束
Never before have we clad strangers in the garb of our own people.
希望这些精灵斗篷能让你们躲过敌人的侦察
May these cloaks help shield you from unfriendly eyes.
兰巴斯
Lembas.
精灵的干粮
Elvish waybread.
只要咬一小口就能让一个成年人填饱肚子
One small bite is enough to fill the stomach of a grown man.
你吃了几块？
How many did you eat?
四块
Four.
你们每向南方走一步就离危险更近一步
Every league you travel south, the danger will increase.
魔多的半兽人占领了安都因河东岸
Mordor Orcs now hold the eastern shore of the Anduin.
但是西岸也并不安全
Nor will you find safety on the western bank.
奇怪的白掌部队曾经出没在我们的边界
Strange creatures bearing the White Hand have been seen on our borders.
半兽人不能在太阳下行动 但是这些怪物却可以
Seldom do Orcs journey in the open under the sun, yet these have done so.
他们在追杀你们
You are being tracked.
只有走水路才有可能赶在敌人前到达拉洛斯瀑布
By river you have the chance of outrunning the enemy to the Falls of Rauros.
我送你的礼物 勒苟拉斯 是凯兰崔姆弓箭
My gift for you, Legolas, is a bow of the Galadhrim.
能让你拥有百步穿杨的绝技
Worthy of the skill of our woodland kin.
这些是诺多伦短剑
These are the daggers of the Noldorin.
曾经在战场上杀敌无数
They have already seen service in war.
千万别害怕 小皮里格林・图克
Do not fear, young Peregrin Took.
你会找到你的勇气
You will find your courage.
送给你的 山姆卫斯・詹吉
And for you, Samwise Gamgee...
希斯蓝制作的精灵之绳
...Elven rope made of hithlain.
谢谢你 女王
Thank you, my lady.
那些漂亮的短剑没有了吗？
Have you run out of those nice, shiny daggers?
那么矮人向精灵要什么礼物？
And what gift would a dwarf ask of the Elves?
什么都不要
Nothing.
我再看凯兰崔尔女王最后一眼就足够了
Except to look upon the lady of the Galadhrim one last time...
因为她比地底蕴藏的所有珠宝都美丽
...for she is more fair than all the jewels beneath the earth.
实际上...
Actually...
我是有一个要求
There was one thing.
不 不 我不能 那太不可能了
No, no, I couldn't. It's quite impossible.
说出来太傻了
Stupid to ask.
我不能再给你什么
I have nothing greater to give...
因为你已拥有最珍贵的礼物
...than the gift you already bear.
那就是亚玟的爱
Am meleth d?n.
我怕亚玟・安多米尔的光芒会黯淡
I ant e-guil Arwen Undómiel…pelitha.
所以我要让她离开中土世界
Aníron i e broniatha,
跟她的族人在一起
ad ae periatham athar i methid en-amar hen.
我会让她坐船到瓦林诺
Aníron i e círatha na Valannor.
她必须面对这个抉择
That choice is yet before her.
你也必须做出决定 阿拉贡
You have your own choice to make, Aragorn.
重建自伊兰迪尔以来你的先祖创造的辉煌成就
To rise above the height of all your fathers since the days of Elendil...
或是带着你仅存的子民坠入绝望的黑暗深渊
...or to fall into darkness with all that is left of your kin.
永别了
Namárie.
还有很多你要做的事情
Nadath na i moe cerich.
我们将不会再见面...
Dan ú-'eveditham
伊力萨
Elessar.
再会了 佛罗多・巴金斯
Farewell, Frodo Baggins.
我送给你埃兰迪尔之光...
I give you the light of E?rendil...
我们最挚爱的星辰
...our most beloved star.
愿它在所有光亮熄灭时...
May it be a light for you in dark places...
在黑暗中为你带来光明
... when all other lights go out.
这次离别带给我的伤痛最深...
I have taken my worst wound at this parting...
因为这是我最后一次看到最美丽的女王
...having looked my last upon that which is fairest.
以后我不会说什么东西美丽除了她的礼物
Henceforth I will call nothing fair unless it be her gift to me.
她送你什么礼物？
What was her gift?
我向她要一根她头上的金发
I asked her for one hair from her golden head.
她给了我三根
She gave me three.
咕噜 他从摩瑞亚矿坑一直在跟踪我们
Gollum. He has tracked us since Moria.
我以为在河上就能甩掉他
I had hoped we would lose him on the river.
可是他的水性很好
But he's too clever a waterman.
如果他把我们的行踪告诉敌人
And if he alerts the enemy to our whereabouts...
我们想要渡河就会更危险
...it will make the crossing even more dangerous.
吃点东西吧 佛罗多先生
Have some food, Mr. Frodo.
不要 山姆
No, Sam.
你一整天都没吃过东西
You haven't eaten anything all day.
你也睡得很不安稳 别以为我没注意到
You're not sleeping, neither. Don't think I haven't noticed.
佛罗多先生...
Mr. Frodo...
我很好
I'm all right.
你并不好
But you're not.
我是来帮你的
I'm here to help you.
我答应甘道夫我会的
I promised Gandalf that I would.
你帮不了我 山姆
You can't help me, Sam.
这次不行
Not this time.
去睡吧
Get some sleep.
到米那斯提力斯比较安全
Minas Tirith is the safer road.
我们可以在那里养精蓄锐
You know that. From there we can regroup.
然后一鼓作气攻向魔多
Strike out for Mordor from a place of strength.
刚铎也帮不了我们
There is no strength in Gondor that can avail us.
你倒是很愿意相信精灵
You were quick enough to trust the Elves.
你对自己的子民一点信心都没有吗？
Have you so little faith in your own people?
对 他们是很软弱 他们意志薄弱
Yes, there is weakness. There is frailty.
但是人类之中也有勇气和荣誉
But there is courage also, and honor to be found in Men.
可是你都看不到
But you will not see that.
你很害怕！
You are afraid!
你这辈子都躲在阴影下
All your life, you have hidden in the shadows.
不敢承认你自己的身份
Scared of who you are, of what you are.
我不会把魔戒带到你的城市
I will not lead the Ring within a hundred leagues of your city.
佛罗多
Frodo.
亚苟那斯巨像
The Argonath.
我一直都想仰望的老国王
Long have I desired to look upon the kings of old.
我的先祖
My kin.
天一黑我们就渡湖
We cross the lake at nightfall.
把船藏好再步行
Hide the boats and continue on foot.
我们从北边进入魔多
We approach Mordor from the North.
是吗？
Oh, yes?
只要通过爱明莫尔就行了...
Just a simple matter of finding our way through Emyn Muil...
那是充满尖石的迷宫
...an impassable labyrinth of razor-sharp rocks.
然后呢 就更好走了
And after that, it gets even better.
那儿有一望无际的臭沼泽地
Festering, stinking marshland as far as the eye can see.
那就是我们的路
That is our road.
我建议你休息一下养精蓄锐 矮人大师
I suggest you take some rest and recover your strength, Master Dwarf.
养精蓄锐个头
Recover my--
我们应该马上走
We should leave now.
不行
No.
半兽人在巡逻东岸 我们一定要等到天黑再出发
Orcs patrol the eastern shore. We must wait for cover of darkness.
我担心的不是东岸
It is not the eastern shore that worries me.
我心中一直有一个阴影和威胁
A shadow and a threat has been growing in my mind.
有什么正在接近 我感觉得到
Something draws near. I can feel it.
养精蓄锐？别理他 小哈比人
Recover strength? Pay no heed to that, young Hobbit.
佛罗多呢？
Where's Frodo?
我们都不该一个人乱跑
None of us should wander alone.
尤其是你
You, least of all.
你的责任重大
So much depends on you.
佛罗多？
Frodo?
我知道你为什么想独自待着
I know why you seek solitude.
我每天都看着你受苦
You suffer. I see it day by day.
你确定你不是白白受苦吗？
You sure you do not suffer needlessly?
还有其它的路 佛罗多
There are other ways, Frodo.
我们可以走另一条路
Other paths that we might take.
我知道你想说什么
I know what you would say.
好像很有道理 但我得到警告
It would seem like wisdom but for the warning in my heart.
警告？警告什么？
Warning? Against what?
我们都很害怕 佛罗多
We're all afraid, Frodo.
但如果让恐惧摧毁一切希望...
But to let that fear drive us, to destroy what hope we have...
未免太不值得了吧？
...don't you see that is madness?
没有别的路可走
There is no other way.
我只想得到捍卫我的子民的力量！
I ask only for the strength to defend my people!
只要你把魔戒借给我
lf you would but lend me the Ring.
不行
No.
为什么你要退缩？我又不是强盗
Why do you recoil? I am no thief.
你失去了理智
You are not yourself.
你以为你有什么机会？
What chance do you think you have?
他们会找到你 他们会抢走魔戒
They will find you. They will take the Ring.
然后你会求生不能 求死不得！
And you will beg for death before the end!
你这傻瓜！
You fool!
你只是靠运气得到它！它应该是我的
It is not yours, save by unhappy chance! It could have been mine.
它应该是我的！把它给我！
It should be mine! Give it to me!
把它给我！
Give it to me!
不！
No!
把它给我！
Give it to me!
不！
No.
我知道了
I see your mind.
你会把魔戒交给索伦！
You will take the Ring to Sauron!
你会背叛我们！
You will betray us!
你会害我们跟你一起死！
You'll go to your death, and the death of us all!
诅咒你！诅咒你和所有的半身人！
Curse you! Curse you and all the halflings!
佛罗多？
Frodo?
佛罗多
Frodo.
我做了什么？
What have I done?
求求你 佛罗多
Please, Frodo.
佛罗多 对不起！
Frodo, I'm sorry!
佛罗多？
Frodo?
它蛊惑了波罗莫
It has taken Boromir.
魔戒呢？
Where is the Ring?
别过来！
Stay away!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
我发誓要保护你
I swore to protect you.
你能保证你不会害我吗？
Can you protect me from yourself?
你会摧毁它吗？
Would you destroy it?
阿拉贡
Aragorn.
伊力萨
Elessar.
我愿意跟随你到最后
I would have gone with you to the end.
跟随到魔多烈焰
Into the very fires of Mordor.
我知道了
I know.
好好照顾他们 尤其是山姆 他不会理解
Look after the others. Especially Sam. He will not understand.
快走 佛罗多！
Go, Frodo!
快跑
Run.
快跑！
Run!
佛罗多先生！
Mr. Frodo!
找到半身人！
Find the halfling!
伊兰迪尔！
Elendil!
阿拉贡 快走！
Aragorn, go!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
躲过来 快！
Hide here. Quick!
快啊！
Come on!
他在干嘛？
What's he doing?
他要走了
He's leaving.
不！
No!
皮聘！
Pippin!
跑 佛罗多 快跑！
Run, Frodo. Go on!
嘿！嘿 你！我在这里！
Hey! Hey, you! Over here!
嘿！
Hey!
我在这里！
Over here!
这里啊！
This way!
成功了！
It's working!
我知道啦！快跑！
I know it's working! Run!
刚铎的号角
The horn of Gondor.
波罗莫
Boromir.
跑！快跑！
Run!
不
No.
他们把小个子抓走了
They took the little ones.
别动
Hold still.
佛罗多 佛罗多在哪里？
Frodo. Where is Frodo?
我让佛罗多走了
I let Frodo go.
你做到我做不到的事
Then you did what I could not.
我试图抢走魔戒
I tried to take the Ring from him.
现在谁也抢不走魔戒了
The Ring is beyond our reach now.
原谅我
Forgive me.
我没有想到
I did not see it.
我让大家失望了
I have failed you all.
不 波罗莫
No, Boromir.
你很英勇
You fought bravely.
你维护了你的荣誉
You have kept your honor.
算了
Leave it.
都结束了
It is over.
人类世界将灭亡 黑暗将笼罩大地...
The world of Men will fall. And all will come to darkness...
我的城市将遭毁灭
...and my city to ruin.
我不知道我有多少力量...
I do not know what strength is in my blood...
但我发誓绝不会让白城沦陷...
...but I swear to you, I will not let the White City fall...
也不会让我们的子民失败
...nor our people fail.
我们的子民
Our people.
我愿跟随你 我的兄弟
I would have followed you, my brother.
我的领袖
My captain.
我的国王
My king.
安息吧...
Be at peace...
刚铎之子
...son of Gondor.
他们在白塔等待他的归来
They will look for his coming from the White Tower.
但是他永远不会回去了
But he will not return.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
我真希望魔戒没在我手中
I wish the Ring had never come to me.
真希望这一切都没发生
I wish none of this had happened.
每个人遇到难关都会这么想...
So do all who live to see such times...
但是那不由我们决定
...but that is not for them to decide.
我们所能决定的是...
All you have to decide...
在给予我们的时间内去做什么
...is what to do with the time that is given to you.
佛罗多 不要走！
Frodo, no!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
佛罗多先生！
Mr. Frodo!
不 山姆
No, Sam.
回去吧 山姆！
Go back, Sam!
我要独自去魔多
I'm going to Mordor alone.
你当然要去
Of course you are.
但我要跟你一起去！
And I'm coming with you!
你不会游泳！
You can't swim!
山姆！
Sam!
我许下一个承诺 佛罗多先生
I made a promise, Mr. Frodo.
一个承诺 千万别离开他 山姆卫斯・詹吉
A promise: "Don't you leave him, Samwise Gamgee."
我绝不会离开你
And I don't mean to.
绝对不会
I don't mean to.
山姆
Sam.
来吧
Come on.
快！佛罗多和山姆就快到东岸了
Hurry! Frodo and Sam have reached the eastern shore.
你不想跟着他们
You mean not to follow them.
佛罗多的命运已经不由我们掌握
Frodo's fate is no longer in our hands.
一切都是徒劳 远征队失败了
Then it has all been in vain. The Fellowship has failed.
只要我们彼此真诚就不是徒劳
Not if we hold true to each other.
我们不会丢下梅里和皮聘让他们受苦而死
We will not abandon Merry and Pippin to torment and death.
只要我们还有力气
Not while we have strength left.
把用不着的东西留下来
Leave all that can be spared behind.
我们轻装而行
We travel light.
让我们猎杀半兽人吧
Let us hunt some Orc.
好！
Yes!
魔多
Mordor.
希望其他人走的路比较安全
I hope the others find a safer road.
神行客会照顾他们的
Strider will look after them.
我想我们不会再见到他们了
I don't suppose we'll ever see them again.
也许还会 佛罗多先生
We may yet, Mr. Frodo.
也许会
We may.
山姆...
Sam...
我很高兴你和我一起
...I'm glad you are with me.
导演：彼得・杰克逊
编剧：弗兰・沃尔什
菲利普・博恩斯
彼得・杰克逊
原著：J.R.R・托尔金
制片：巴厘 M. 奥斯博恩
彼得・杰克逊
制片：弗兰・沃尔什
提姆・桑德斯
执行制片：马克・奥德斯凯
鲍勃・韦恩斯坦
哈维・韦恩斯坦
执行制片：罗伯特・沙耶
迈克尔・里尼
摄影导演：安德鲁・莱斯尼
监制：格兰特・梅杰
剪辑：约翰・吉尔伯特
联合制片：里克・博拉斯
加米・塞克里克
伊利亚・伍德 …… 佛罗多・巴金斯
伊安・麦克莱恩 …… 甘道夫
丽芙・泰勒 …… 亚玟
维戈・莫特森 …… 亚拉冈
西恩・奥斯汀 …… 山姆・卫斯詹吉
凯特・布兰切特 …… 精灵女王
约翰・里斯-戴维斯 …… 金霹
比利・博伊德 …… 皮聘
多米尼克・莫纳汉 …… 梅里
奥兰多・布鲁姆 …… 勒苟拉斯
克里斯托弗・李 …… 萨鲁曼
雨果・维文 …… 爱隆王
特别演出：肖恩・宾 …… 波罗莫
和伊安・霍尔姆 …… 比尔博・巴金斯
安迪・瑟金斯 …… 咕噜
马尔顿・索克斯
克里格・哈尔迪
劳伦斯・马克罗
英国选角：约翰・哈伯德
艾米・麦克莱恩
美国选角：维多利亚・伯罗斯
新西兰选角：利滋・穆莱恩
澳大利亚选角：安・罗宾逊
服装设计：尼吉拉・迪克森
理查德・泰勒
作曲与配乐：霍华德・肖
助理制片：埃伦・M. 萨默斯
化妆特效及场景设计：理查德・泰勒
视觉效果总监：乔・莱特瑞
影片主题歌《祝愿》与《希望》
由 恩雅 作曲和演唱